[{"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "How do you integrate external applications to increase efficiency in systems and processes? What applications would you recommend?", "answers": ["The interviewers are looking for your knowledge and experience with tools and applications that essentially help you work smarter, not harder. Check their job description for any tips on what they might prefer and check their website for any potential partners that might offer a relevant application, such as Microsoft Flow.", "\"My favorite application to meet the majority of my needs is Microsoft Flow. I have simplified and even automated a number of processes across my department that have saved countless hours of time. Integrating Flow has improved communication and data-sharing, and it has freed up a significant amount of time for employees to focus on and prioritize more critical elements of their work.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "How are your writing skills?", "answers": ["Many Application Database Administrator positions will require strong communication skills, particularly writing. This is an opportunity where you can incorporate experience from a range of previous positions. Review the job description for any clues as to what sort of writing skills might be most relevant, such as technical or subject-based.", "\"I have extensive writing experience across several domains, including academic writing, business communication, and reporting analytics. I value attention to detail and tailored communication based on the reader, so I enjoy writing and editing in a variety of capacities.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "Aside from your computer, what is the most frequently used item on your desk?", "answers": ["This question is a fun opportunity for the interviewers to get to know you and how you work a little better. Don't be afraid to be a little fun and creative with it! You might put a twist on something practical like your trusty penguin stapler, or something less expected like your llama coffee mug.", "\"The most used item on my desk aside from my computer would have to be my coffee mug. I always have something in it, whether it's coffee, tea, water, or juice. I need at least one beverage on my desk pretty much at all times.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "What about our company interests you the most?", "answers": ["This is another opportunity for you to demonstrate your knowledge and research on the company. If you respond with something a bit more expected, like the company mission, then be sure to know it well and draw a more personal connection. Your interviewers will value your honesty and probably recognize if you are sharing what you think they want to hear. Do your research on the company to help you better answer this as authentically as possible.", "\"I am most interested in and inspired by the company's determination. As an industry leader, this company strives for greatness daily and does so by respecting and valuing employees and the community it serves. The mission and vision of the company welcome challenge and opportunity in a bold and refreshing way, and I admire that. I am very interested in supporting the company and playing an integral part in driving innovation forward.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "Is there anything in the position's job description that surprises you?", "answers": ["This question serves as both a test and an opportunity to provide any necessary clarification. The interviewers want to ensure that you have taken the time to thoroughly process the position description, and they also want to clear up any potential confusion or misunderstanding about the role prior to the start. Come prepared with a copy of the job description or a few key points written down. If you don't have anything that particularly surprises you, then you might share a component of the position that you are most looking forward to.", "\"Given my experience in this role and my understanding of the company, nothing in the job description particularly surprises me. I was very excited to see the value the company places on professional development opportunities for staff, so I greatly look forward to learning and growing in the role, organization, and overall industry.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "How do you ensure data integrity across multiple systems and domains?", "answers": ["There are many influences that might impact data integrity, such as changes to data due to storage, an error in processing or retrieving, hardware failure, human error, or even hacking. The interviewers want to ensure that you are aware of the various factors that might impact data integrity as well as how thoroughly you attempt to address it.", "\"There are many factors that might impact data integrity, from something as simple as human error to something a bit more complex like hardware failure. To stay on top of it all, I maintain a few key touchpoints. I maintain a log of everyone that has access to the data including their titles and access levels. I run bi-weekly audits to verify the integrity of our most up-to-date data and help resolve any human error. I also follow the status sites of all relevant systems and domains to stay current on any potential outages or failures. I have found that this comprehensive approach resolves most errors and maintains data integrity.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "What are your top three skills or strengths that best qualify you for this position?", "answers": ["For a question like this, you'll want to have done a side-by-side comparison of the job description and your resume. Identify the top skills or qualities needed and desired for the position, and highlight where they appear on your resume. Don't be afraid to bring in out-of-industry positions - you can always make a case for transferrable skills to be incredibly relevant. If the skills on your resume don't quite reflect what is needed for the position, then share skills that are as relevant as possible and - if true - include your ability to learn and adapt quickly and seamlessly.", "\"My top three skills include: keen attention to detail, communication, and documentation. Over the last 8 years, I have continually refined each of these skills in a range of positions, so I am very confident employing them in my work. More specifically, I value the importance of all three skills when it comes to analytics and reporting, which I understand to be particularly relevant to this position.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "How often should you back-up a company database?", "answers": ["In order to save and protect as much valuable data as possible, many companies will back-up their data anywhere from every 24 hours to once per week. The frequency of back-ups might depend on the size and profile of the company and the nature of the stored information, though it is uncommon to see a company back-up any less frequently than once per week. Consider the company you're interested in - a large company like Amazon or Microsoft might back-up every 24 hours, while a smaller start-up company or nonprofit might back-up once or twice a week. When answering this question, safely share a range of the maximum and minimum times you'd back-up a database in a given period of time.", "\"In my experience primarily working in small-to-medium-sized companies, I have found the need to back-up our systems and databases once per week. That said, I recognize the potential risk of waiting up to a week to back-up data, so I would generally recommend at least twice per week.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "In your opinion, why is user access knowledge important in database security?", "answers": ["User access knowledge is pretty straightforward: who has access to your database? The interviewers want to test your awareness of the importance of knowing this as well as what you might do to maintain the most up-to-date knowledge of who has access. Share why you feel user access knowledge is important for database security as well as what steps you take to track who has what access at which levels and at what times.", "\"It is exceptionally important to be aware of exactly who has access to your databases as well as their level and frequency of access. The more you know about user access knowledge, the better you're able to triage issues and address them quickly as soon as they arise.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "Give us an example of proactive - and reactive - data management support you've employed.", "answers": ["The more proactive data management measures are put in place, the fewer reactive data management measures are needed. This question touches on many other topics that will be mentioned in the interview, such as user access knowledge, database security, data integrity, and so on. The interviewers are looking for how well you integrate all of these components to best support data/base management. Demonstrate how thoroughly you practice proactive measures as well as how well prepared you are for inevitable reactive measures.", "\"I run regular audits to ensure data integrity across systems. In my audits, I often come across a handful of errors that I'm able to correct before they get buried or forgotten, so I've found this to be a particularly powerful proactive measure. When I run into a challenge with database security, my first reactive measure is always to cross-reference my user access spreadsheet with database login history. This helps me to identify whether or not the security issue is from an internal or external source, and I can run further checks from there.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "If a manager requests a tight turnaround on a report that you know takes longer to pull than your deadline allows, then what do you do?", "answers": ["The interviewers are interested in how diplomatically you handle a situation in which a superior asks for something you cannot fulfill. This is an opportunity to demonstrate your interpersonal communication skills and share how you have handled this before or how you would anticipate handling it.", "\"In order for them to understand part of the process and plan accordingly, I would inform them that unfortunately there are system constraints that require a minimum of whatever time is needed. I would inquire about how I might best be able to support the project and share the earliest date the report could be available.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "What experience do you have with using a database to track and maintain an event?", "answers": ["Depending on the company and nature of the specific role, you might need to assist in tracking data for real-time events. Data might be pulled from multiple sources and change often. If you are asked this question, then a portion of your position will likely include tracking dynamic, real-time data. This is also a great question to emphasize the importance of data integrity and security which will also come up at other points during your interview.", "\"I have used a couple of databases and web-based systems to track and maintain event information for gatherings of 10 to 100 people present. Pre-event, I've collected RSVPs, updated constituent information in our records, and used RSVP data to inform and action on other components of the event. During the event, I utilize the databases to update information and attendance in real-time. After the event, I make any final changes in the database and constituent records. Throughout the process, I communicate with invited guests and relevant parties through web-based systems that I have synced with our databases to allow easy, streamlined communication.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "What are the top 3 qualities you look for in a team?", "answers": ["This question is to understand how you view working on a team as well as what you look for in a team. Many companies recognize the importance of team cohesion and team culture as being a factor in the hiring process, so they will want to ensure that you and the team will work well with one another and get along. When answering this question, be truthful about what you look for - you can follow-up at the end of the interview by asking how they would describe the team you'd be working on.", "\"I think many qualities can make a great team. I most value strong and honest communication, desire to collaborate, and trust. None of these qualities are automatically given - they take time and effort to develop. When a team has achieved an ability to authentically tap into each of these qualities, then I believe they can accomplish great things.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "Tell us about how you've collaborated across teams or departments to complete a project or to meet a goal.", "answers": ["When you work in a role like Application Database Administrator, you might often be asked to provide data and reports for various departments. Your interviewers are interested in your ability to work with individuals outside of your department and to collaborate and meet goals on time. You likely see these individuals less often than those in your own department, so be sure to identify potential barriers and how you've overcome them and worked together to be successful.", "\"I have often found the need to collaborate with individuals outside of my team or department, and I always enjoy those opportunities. A great example is when I worked across 4 different departments to organize and execute an event for nearly 120 employees. Once the core team was established, we determined our timeline, deadlines, meeting schedule, and standards for communication. We made sure to touch on as many components of the project that would steer us to success as possible, and we held each other accountable to our tasks and goals. Over the course of 3 months, we were able to stay on target and allow room to course-correct as needed. As a result, we seamlessly and successfully held the event and received positive feedback on our post-event survey.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "When working from your desk for extended periods of time, what do you need to be comfortable and successful?", "answers": ["Many companies are becoming increasingly aware of the impact desk-time can have on employees, and they might make considerations for your space as a result. For example, they might provide you with a standing desk, a special chair, or a location with easy access to certain facilities in the building. If they ask, then don't be afraid to let them know what you might need - within reason, of course.", "\"I like to have a bit of flexibility with my workspace, especially when I'm utilizing it for extended periods of time. In particular, I really value the option of a standing desk so I may choose to get on my feet and stay focused when I feel myself starting to slouch. I also never underestimate the value of a stress ball. Sometimes, I need to physically engage myself a bit to get my ideas flowing, and something as simple as a stress ball can support that.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "Describe a difficult project where you successfully met or exceeded expectations.", "answers": ["This is a common interview question for many positions and fields, so be prepared to answer something along these lines. It can help to write down a response to this question prior to your interview to bring with you. To hit all of the components and share them methodically, use the STAR (situation, task, action, result) structure. Consider an example that is relatable to the position and will allow the interviewers to see you in the role.", "\"I was once tasked with leading a project that was entirely outside of the realm of my position description that involved preparing a 7 piece mailing in-house for 500 individuals. I was given guidance on how to prepare the 7 components which included collaborating with individuals from a different team. My first step was to create a timeline and a list of action items to ensure that I didn't miss a step that could derail the project. I contacted all parties involved and informed them of the timeline and their tasks. I added a decent amount of buffer time in my deadlines to allow for error since this was an unfamiliar project for me. Once I had that ball rolling, I booked a conference room for an afternoon to allow me the time and space to fully prepare this mailing in-house. Then, I contacted the volunteer coordinator to recruit some support for physically putting the mailing together. I maintained regular contact and checked-in with everyone involved to ensure a smooth process. As a result of my planning, communication, and accountability, I was able to complete the project a full 4 days ahead of schedule with no errors.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "How would your former colleagues describe your teamwork?", "answers": ["This question offers the interviewers insight as to how you view teamwork as well as how well you integrate and collaborate with others. Team cohesion is a big consideration for many employers, so your interviewers will want to understand how well you work with others and how your involvement is perceived by teammates. Consider the various roles a member of a team might have and where you fit - are you an outspoken leader, an examiner/inquirer, a doer, or something else?", "\"My former colleagues would likely describe me as a team member that listens and observes, seeks clarification, and then provides collaborative suggestions. I rarely start off sharing my ideas, because I like to synthesize what I hear from everyone in the group and try to offer collaborative solutions. I believe my former colleagues find me to be a fairly flexible team member, so I can move around based on what is most needed, whether it's leading a particular project, act on given directions, or support in some other way.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "What are you most interested in when it comes to this role at our company?", "answers": ["This is an opportunity for you to demonstrate what you know about the position and the company. Look for how the position description might include a particularly unique component to the role that you haven't seen elsewhere, or consider how you might look forward to providing a direct contribution to a particular aspect of the company mission. Your interviewers are interested in what excites you about fulfilling this role at their company, specifically, so you'll want to emphasize how this role at this company is valuable to you.", "\"I am really looking forward to the way in which this role contributes so directly to the company's mission and vision from behind the scenes. I appreciate having the ability to support a company at such a foundational level while doing something I deeply enjoy. I also recognize that this role allows for a great deal of learning across various departments in the company and creates opportunities for growth and mobility.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "Where do you aspire to be professionally 5 years from now?", "answers": ["This is an opportunity for you to share your professional goals and development aspirations with your interviewers. You will want to demonstrate a genuine interest in growth, and it will likely help to do some research on how you might grow within the industry or company, itself. It is always important to check in with yourself prior to interviews to identify how your response to this might've adapted over time - do you want to be at a particular company, in a particular industry, or are you still ironing out the details?", "\"In 5 years, I hope to have a greater understanding of the company and the opportunities in which I might be able to grow and support. I aspire to gain the knowledge and experience to earn more responsibility within this department and manage more projects. Above all, I look forward to an opportunity to explore more of what potential trajectories this position might take me.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "What professional development do you think might be most beneficial to you and to this position over the next 3 years?", "answers": ["This question can provide both you and the interviewers with a great deal of information. If the interviewers show interest in your professional development, particularly year-over-year, then that can indicate that they value your growth and might incorporate professional development opportunities in their planning. Your answer will help them understand how much you've thought about your career trajectory in this particular role or field as well as the level of seriousness you might take your professional development. If you aren't sure how to answer this question, then be sure to share that you are actively searching for development opportunities as you solidify where you will be based.", "\"I would welcome any professional development available to me as it relates to this company and industry. For this position specifically, I am aware of a few regularly-held webinars that offer new tips and tricks to streamline workflows and maximize database maintenance. I find it useful to attend webinars from time to time to keep current on applications and databases, and they're great at providing a lot of useful information in a short period of time. In addition to webinars, there are a handful of yearly regional conferences that explore new offerings in technology for systems and databases, so I would, of course, appreciate any opportunity to expand my knowledge and awareness in that capacity.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "What steps do you take to appropriately handle confidential information? Please give us an example.", "answers": ["Any position that interacts with databases will inevitably encounter confidential information. Some of it might be electronic, and some might be physical documents. Your interviewers want to ensure that you are mindful of even the small details, so don't overthink your answer and don't hesitate to share a fairly simple answer.", "\"Handling confidential information can involve measures as simple as crossing through information or shredding, and it can be more complex with encryption and security access levels. An example I come across often is handling documentation with credit card and bank numbers. Given the nature of the documentation, we have to file it away for future auditing purposes, so we can't simply shred it. Instead, we keep the files in a secure area while processing takes place. Once processing is complete and we no longer require the number, I simply black-out the credit card information with a sharpie before filing it away for future audits. From there, individuals with proper clearances may access the general information without knowledge of their financial details. It is a simple measure to handle and protect confidential information, but it goes a long way.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "With technology advancing daily, how do you stay up-to-date on new products and trends?", "answers": ["You will not be expected to know everything about technology in this role, obviously. Your interviewers want to gauge how current you are on developments in technology and how thoroughly you explore new things. As it pertains to this role, it can be helpful to share any forums or online communities you find useful to stay up-to-date on relevant software. You want to demonstrate that you are open to adaptation and simplifying systems.", "\"There are so many ways to try to stay up-to-date, so I try to diversify my sources of information. I join official online forums for any software I use in my position so I can learn from others in the field, and I often catch new releases and announcements straight from the source. I also attend webinars quarterly to catch-up on new tips and tricks that might help streamline workflows and processes. My greatest takeaway from working in this industry is that adaptability and efficiency are key, so I welcome new information and ideas.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "What databases do you have the most experience using?", "answers": ["There are many kinds of databases, applications, and interfaces, and the interviewers are looking to ensure that your experience is thorough and relevant enough. Pay close attention to the position description and research the company to help guarantee that the experience you share is most beneficial to the role.", "\"I have experience with a range of databases serving a number of functions. Most of my experience pertains to social services and education including data on clients, constituents, and students. The primary databases I've used in my career include Raiser's Edge, ETO, DHS, and IRIS. I have extensive experience using each of these databases over the last several years, which I recognize is an asset to this particular position given their relevance to your industry.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "What is your ideal work environment?", "answers": ["Office spaces and working environments can vary by company and have a big impact on motivating employees. Some employers are becoming much more open to working remotely compared to recent years and often offer incentives for office-based work, such as free food, communal lounge spaces, and even game rooms. Depending on the company and the position, desk spaces might be tightly clustered or more isolated. Do research on the company prior to your interview for any information as to how their office spaces might be laid out to help inform your answer.", "\"I enjoy working in a dynamic environment where I might be able to bounce ideas off of colleagues around me while also having the option of honing in on my work independently. I tend to enjoy the opportunity to connect with my coworkers in shared spaces, like a break room. I find it important to feel a sense of community with coworkers to facilitate greater understanding and collaboration, so I always appreciate a work environment that promotes that.\""]}, {"topic": "Application+Database+Administrator", "question": "What do you do for 'screen breaks' when you've been at your desk for an extended period of time?", "answers": ["Computer-heavy positions can lead to eye strain, headaches, body aches, and so on. It can be helpful, often expected, to step away for a few minutes to take a quick 'screen break.' You might go refill your water bottle, grab some coffee, stretch, or simply take a quick walk around the block. The goal here is to share an example that does not necessarily indicate that you would spend significant time away from your computer. Instead, share how a quick action or activity can help make you more focused and productive.", "\"I have found that quickly stepping away from my computer has been hugely helpful in my longevity throughout the day. I try to mix up my 'screen breaks' depending on what I need, though they almost entirely involve getting my body moving in some way. Sometimes, it's as simple as walking to the break room to fill up my water bottle and grab a cup of coffee, or I might get some fresh air with a 5-minute walk around the block. If I just need to get my body moving, I'll even pause for a quick stretch at my desk. Just 1 to 5 minutes of moving aroundcan make a big difference when I return to my desk and get back to work.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "Describe the pros and cons of using shorter call-to-action forms vs. longer CTA forms.", "answers": ["The interviewer asks questions like this to test your strategic knowledge within your role. Different employees may have different needs within the organization. Being able to explain the pros and cons of a change can help you to find compromises that keep everyone happy.", "\"Typically, shorter CTA forms see higher completion, but longer CTA forms offer more information that we can use to qualify leads early.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "Do you use a swipe file?", "answers": ["A swipe file is copy industry jargon for 'headlines that work.' Copywriters and marketers tend to assemble a swipe file over the course of a career, and you'll see these same headlines over and over. For example, 'New Year, New You' is a common headline that marketers will use around the turn of the year in a variety of industries. The interviewer wants to know if you've been creating a swipe file over the course of your career.", "\"I have a swipe file for email headlines and landing page headlines that have shown a consistently high open rate and conversion rate throughout my career.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "What research tools do you use to determine what to test?", "answers": ["Conversion Rate Optimization often requires a lot of software. Questions like these help the interviewer determine what additional expenses might be associated with your hire and whether or not you have experience in the tools they already use. Explaining how you'd use these tools to enhance your performance is crucial.", "\"I use CrazyEgg, Zarget, HotJar and similar tools to monitor heatmaps and interaction prior to and during A/B tests. It's very important to qualitatively analyze pages prior to testing so that we're not analyzing parts of the page that seem to be performing adequately.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "Describe some microconversions that you might use inside a shopping cart.", "answers": ["This question is intended to tease out your deeper understanding of conversion rate optimization. Microconversions are actions-which-lead-to-conversion. For example, if your customer receives an email with a link in it to a purchase page, clicking the link and making a purchase would be conversions. In this case, a microconversion might be scrolling the page (e.g. not immediately bouncing) or submitting payment information.", "\"Some common microconversions for shopping cart optimization would be things like setting product quantity, adding shipping or billing information,  or adding a payment method. These actions directly indicate that the user is closer to purchase than they were before, so they're microconversions.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "Describe the elements of a perfect landing page.", "answers": ["If you can't describe all the elements of a landing page, how will you know how to break up your tests? Typically, you won't see any conversion lift from changing two or three words in a single feature or benefit on the page, but you might very-well see a conversion list by reorganizing your entire features and benefits section. It's common practice to test each of these elements independently.", "\"The elements of a perfect landing page are a strong headline, unique selling proposition, features/benefits that answer a consumer's pain points, a video showing use, social proof, a closing argument, and a call to action.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "How would you test the earliest stages of a marketing funnel?", "answers": ["This question tests your understanding of marketing funnels. The first question being asked is, 'what's the earliest stage of a marketing funnel?' The second question is, 'what would you test for there?'", "\"What's most important in the earliest stages of the marketing funnel, which are generally responsible for collecting warm, unqualified leads, is the quality of leads. I'd test the earliest stages of the marketing funnel using a performance indicator like the percentage of new leads that became qualified leads.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "What sort of results can we expect from Conversion Rate Optimization?", "answers": ["Conversion Rate Optimization tends to be a revenue-generating function. Business leaders weigh the cost of your employment against the projected increase in conversion rate. If the increase in conversion rate you can bring is higher than your cost of employment, you'll be hired. If not, you won't.", "\"For a company of your size with no previous conversion rate optimization, we would expect to see a conversion rate lift across the board, from email opens to landing page conversions to shopping cart value. This usually results in a 20% to 40% compounded annual growth rate.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "Where do you typically look for low hanging fruit to optimize?", "answers": ["CRO tends to be the sort of role where your value increases with time. It's likely your employer will be taking a loss on your costs initially that they hope to recoup in the future as their advertising budgets increase. Offering some immediate benefits that can start earning them money with little or no spin-up will help soften the blow of your cost.", "\"I took a look at several of your landing pages, and I noticed a lot of non-critical information being captured on your forms. For instance, your sign-up form asks for the user's age and gender. Unless your profitability depends heavily on these two factors, you could collect this information later, when the user is more engaged.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "What software do you use to perform A/B tests?", "answers": ["This question usually gets one of two specific groups of answers. In the first group, you have what I'd call the 'enterprise' platforms: Adobe Target, FullStory, Optimize, etc. In the second group, you have the 'startup' platforms: ClickFunnels, Google Experiments, Unbounce, and other freemium platforms. The interviewing is trying to understand if your background in CRO software matches what they have or can afford.", "\"In the past, I've worked exclusively with startups and SMBs on conversion rate optimization, so the software I recommend includes a combination of Google Experiments and Unbounce, along with the A/B testing platform provided by your email service provider. That should let us test the key components of your marketing strategy without breaking the bank.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "How many tests do you run on a landing page to ensure its optimized?", "answers": ["This question dives into the methodology behind your conversion rate optimization. Being able to answer this question sufficiently doesn't necessarily mean giving the correct number of tests, but, instead, showing that you have a plan. Knowing your own process for conversion rate optimization, and explaining it here, will ensure that you don't 'float' between projects that are showing increasingly diminishing returns.", "\"As long as tests are still producing results, we'll continue running them. Typically, there are seven major elements on a landing page that need to be tested. I typically recommend seven tests as a minimum and an average between 15 and 20. It's not worth continuing if you can't achieve better than 5 or 10% lift from your previous conversion rate in two consecutive tests.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "How do you pre-test conversion rate on pages not yet receiving traffic?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to see what your process for concept and creative testing is. Since it's expensive and time consuming to approve a public landing page in a large organization, as much testing as possible happens before the page ever goes public. If you've done concept and creative testing before, now's the time to shine.", "\"When pretesting concepts for landing pages, I like to do one-on-one interviews and focus groups on the above-the-fold content. Getting feedback about copy and graphics prior to launching can save a lot of time and effort.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "Have you tested PPC ads?", "answers": ["In almost every case, conversion rate optimization includes optimizing pay-per-click and other traffic-generating channels. If you've got a process for testing Google Ads, that's a bonus. If you have worked with other ad networks and tested ad creative across several types of media, you're a home run candidate.", "\"In addition to Google Ads Search and Display, I've tested and optimized Sponsored Amazon Listings.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "Have you done any design work?", "answers": ["This question is intended to inform the interviewer about your understanding of UI/UX for landing pages. While Conversion Rate Optimizers rarely, if ever, do the design for landing pages, it's critical that you can communicate changes with a designer. You may be expected to do light design, particularly image selection and editing.", "\"I've worked with designers my whole career, but I don't design landing pages. I can work with and edit templates and completed designs.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "What are some types of ROI that wouldn\u2019t commonly show up in your data?", "answers": ["This question aims to understand your strategic chops. Marketing often bends the metrics we aren't watching. Explain your understanding of these other benefits to conversion optimization.", "\"There are dozens of hidden metrics that we can't easily test. For example, a longer landing page might lead to more brand identification or understanding. In cases like this, if going to a shorter page doesn't show hard data of a significantly increased ROI, we can use our intuition to select between two otherwise-equal pages.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "How would you test a page intended to qualify leads?", "answers": ["This question asks about marketing-qualified leads, or MQLs. This is typically the final stage in marketing before a sales team actively takes the reins on managing the lead. After the sales team gets the lead, they'll either agree that the lead is qualified (it becomes a SQL) or they'll disagree. A strong and accurate qualification page ensures a high MQL:SQL ratio.", "\"On a page with the goal of qualifying leads, there are a few key metrics to look at. Obviously, the number of people who complete the page is important. Beyond that, the accuracy of the qualification process would be the second thing I would test: how many marketing-qualified leads became sales-qualified?\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "How would you optimize a social commerce post?", "answers": ["This question is simply asking about how to test organic traffic channels. You can respond the same way you would to questions about testing blog posts. Set a key performance indicator and measure it.", "\"The key performance indicators for social posts are reach, engagement, and purchase.  I'd test and optimize each independently.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "How would you report the results of a conversion test?", "answers": ["In Conversion Rate Optimization jobs, it's your responsibility to prove your value. Becoming an expert at organizing and reporting results from tests is the key to keeping the corporate beancounters happy. Give a description here about how you'd report individual test results as well as collate tests into a digestible dashboard.", "\"I usually track the results of day-to-day tests in an Excel document and prepare a monthly report of all tests and their conversion lifts.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "How do you stay organized?", "answers": ["A conversion rate optimization job requires a high level of organization and attention to detail. It's not uncommon for a CRO specialist to be running twenty or thirty tests at any given time, so keeping track of these tests is paramount. Not to mention, all the tests you've run have data and analysis to support them, and these results should inform your future decisions. Explain your strategy for keeping on top of so much data.", "\"Excel is my number one tool for managing ongoing tests. After assigning every test a number, I log the duration, results, and relevant links into Excel.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "What is your technical background?", "answers": ["As with any digital marketing specialty, CRO practitioners are often doing some advanced computing to gather the data they need. This most often includes installing or troubleshooting javascript tracking snippets. You might also need to perform more unique tasks like logging in remotely to a specialized data processing computer.", "\"I'm proficient in basic Javascript and have experience with dozens of different software platforms.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "How would you structure a conversion rate audit of our entire marketing department?", "answers": ["This is a big question. It's likely intended to qualify you for a senior or director-level position. It'd be impossible to dive into the details in an interview, so keep your answer focused on the process of doing an audit.", "\"I can assure you that my process of conversion rate auditing is sufficient to audit an entire marketing department. I'd start by researching and building an inventory of your marketing assets. Then, I'd identify KPIs for each of the assets and ensure that the KPI is being tracked. Then, I'd use industry benchmarks to determine which, if any of the assets are obviously underperforming. I'd start testing with the most obvious candidates and use what we learn to inform our tests going forward.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "Do you have a background in copywriting/editing?", "answers": ["It's not uncommon for a conversion rate optimization specialist to rewrite headlines or body copy during tests. If you have experience writing headlines, particularly as a copywriter, definitely lean on that during the interview. If you have results from headlines you've rewritten, those are a nice share, too.", "\"I used to work in PPC marketing, where I wrote the headline and subhead for all our ads. In just days after I joined the team, the variation I wrote on our most popular ad increased their results by 10%.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "Do you have a background in HTML/CSS?", "answers": ["Light HTML/CSS is expected from a CRO specialist, since it would be far too expensive/time consuming to bring in a developer to do things like moving a block of text around on the page. If you don't have an HTML/CSS experience, you can hopefully lean on your experience working with landing page design software.", "\"Yes, I've worked with light HTML/CSS throughout my career. While I'm not a developer, I can make changes to an existing template.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "Do you have a background in eCommerce/Amazon/eBay/etc?", "answers": ["Traditionally, CRO has been more concerned with lead generation than eCommerce. More and more, CRO specialists are being tasked with managing eCommerce listings. Many of the same principles apply, so if you've worked with any of retail eCommerce, aggregators like Amazon, or social commerce, be sure to mention the platforms during your interview.", "\"I've managed Amazon listings and worked in traditional eCommerce for a brand with over 400 SKUs.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "What is your statistical background?", "answers": ["At its core, conversion rate optimization is a statistical discipline. While a number of software suites or platforms will abstract away the statistics for end-users, they might do so erroneously, leading to errors in judgment. A strong background in statistics will help you to understand what the deluge of data actually means.", "\"I took statistics in college and have worked with SPSS to perform statistical analysis on data.\""]}, {"topic": "CRO+Specialist", "question": "Do you have any questions for me?", "answers": ["CRO specialists always slot into a larger organizations and often are replacing an outgoing optimizer. This is a good chance for you to get an idea about what kind of optimization work has already been done at the organization. Ask questions to get a better feel for how your role will affect the larger organization.", "\"Which are your best-performing landing pages or advertisements? What do you like about them?\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Thinking about the different industries you may have worked in, from a data perspective, which company and industry is most similar to the one in which our company competes?", "answers": ["Interviewers would only pose this question if you do not have industry-specific experience related to their company. Without this experience, they want to know how you can apply what you learned from previous positions to the one for which you are interviewing. Be ready to answer this question by conducting research ahead of time.", "\"There are a few similarities between the financial services and healthcare industries, specifically related to data and the work of a Data Analyst. One of the most important is the security of customer or patient data. Both industries work with highly personal and sensitive data that must be kept secure at all times. Because of this, access to data may be more restricted and analyses may require more time to complete as you navigate through all the security.  To be successful as a Data Analyst in these industries, you will need to be, not only organized, but able to present a clear case for the data your analyses require.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Working as a Data Analyst gives you a unique perspective on the data and the tools used while working with that data. Is there a time when you recommended a change to any of the data processes or tools used? Did anything result from your recommendation?", "answers": ["Hiring managers would like to see that you have confidence in your knowledge and experiences as a Data Analyst and that you would take the initiative to recommend a change that would benefit the company.  When sharing the recommendation you made, include as many details as possible, particularly the reason you made it. Do not be hesitant to share a change you recommended that may have not been implemented. It still shows your ability to take initiative and that you are continually considering process improvement.", "\"I believe Data Analysts in non-technical departments are usually the most familiar with the company's data. However, I have worked in companies where data was accessible to several people who were not in an analyst role. This caused much confusion over the interpretation of the data.  While data dictionaries can be helpful in these situations, I believe it provides a limited explanation. I recommended that those in non-analytical jobs rely on Data Analysts for data access. This ensured that data was not misinterpreted which could negatively affect strategies being created. I built a case by identifying examples of when data was misinterpreted. The company implemented my recommendation and was even willing to hire more Data Analysts to make sure that there were enough resources to execute my plan.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "How many years of SQL programming do you have? In your most recent position as a Data Analyst, for what percentage of your analytical projects did you utilize your SQL skills?", "answers": ["SQL is the most well known scripting language, and many believe it is the easiest to learn. To be marketable, Data Analyst should make sure to learn SQL and gain experience using it. This question is straightforward - the interviewer wants to gauge the strength of your SQL programming skills.  If you only have a few years of experience, emphasize how your skills have grown with each subsequent project.", "\"I have 7 years of experience programming with SQL. Over this timespan, I have used SQL to some degree for over 90% of my projects. At times, I have used multiple languages for different phases of projects, but find SQL to be the language I turn to the most.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Think of a project where you were working with a relatively large data set. Describe to me the process you had to take to gather and prepare the data for analysis.", "answers": ["Working with large data sets can present some challenges, so hiring managers want to know that you have the experience to handle them if they arise. Share any challenges you might have faced and how you successfully overcame them. If you have been fortunate enough not to face any challenges, stick to the details of your project and the steps you took while working with the data.", "\"I have had experience working with large data sets delivered to us from outside vendors. Many times these data sets were survey responses for Marketing Research projects with a large sample size. Upon first receiving the data set, I checked the validity of the data by running predetermined frequencies and queries. Doing so would often reveal issues such as missing data, data type issues and errors in skip patterns within the survey. I would work with the vendor to correct these issues before beginning further analyses on the data. Once the data issues were resolved, I would load the data into a data analysis tool to begin my analysis. Sometimes I would work with a Data Engineer to load it into an appropriate tool that could handle the size of the data set.\"", "\"I have worked with large data sets. I have used the data set that is available publicly, therefore, I never got the opportunity to gather them, however, I have to spend a lot of time preparing and cleaning data for analysis.  I start with running some queries for exploratory analysis. By doing this, it reveals issues such as missing data, data type issues, and errors in skip patterns within the survey. If possible, I would reach out to the right person to understand the source of error and come up with the right way to address and resolve these issues before the data analysis. When the issue gets resolved, I would start working with the analysis and always reaching out to the right person if I need some help such as if I need a technology-related issue, I would reach out to DBA or data engineer or if it is domain related issue, then I may reach the knowledge expertise or data steward to understand more and more.\"", "It sounds like you have solid experience working with large datasets, which is great. You've done an excellent job explaining how you have cleaned and prepared data for analysis. You state that you don't have experience in gathering data because all of the data you've worked with to date has been available publically. But even so, didn't you have to take the data from that location? Despite the fact that it's public, you still had to gather and compile it, right? If so, definitely don't discount yourself when it comes to gathering data. Consider rephrasing your answer as seen below.", "\"I have a lot of experience in working with large datasets. I have efficiently gathered and compiled data from publically available sources many times before and have also spent significant time cleaning and preparing data for analysis. In general, I start by running some queries for exploratory purposes. This tends to reveal issues like missing data, mismatched and missing data types, and skip pattern errors. If needed, I reach out to the right person to determine the source of the error and then I devise a way to address and resolve it. Once the issue has been resolved, I start carrying out the analysis, collaborating with various teams as needed.\"", "\"\u2022\tWhen conducting my applied econometrics dissertation, I created a dataset in excel with columns including, year, country, growth rate. The data set was for 70 countries and had around 1750 rows. I verified that each data source was legitimate before using it.\r\n\u2022\tDuring my technology internship, I had to restructure extremely large datasets for our clients to meet the import requirements of the in-house software. I leveraged excel tools such as VLOOKUP\u2019s here to optimize the process.\"", "Great start, and it sounds like you have a lot to work with.  I'd recommend adding more detail to spell out your process.  The question is seeking a step-by-step answer that reveals a sound, accurate process."]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Tell me about the different types of audiences to whom you've presented. Were these presentations done in person or remotely?", "answers": ["Hiring managers look for Data Analysts with strong presentation skills - someone who can present analyses and answer questions clearly and with confidence. It would be ideal if you had experience presenting to an executive level audience, but this is not always necessary. When describing the types of audiences, include approximate size, whether it included executives and possibly what departments within the company were present. For example, in many cases, hiring managers look for candidates that can clearly present their findings to people with different backgrounds. More specifically, experience communicating with both technical and non-technical audiences is a highly valued skill. With the rise of remote work, some hiring managers will want to know if you have experience presenting analyses via phone or video conference calls, since these types of presentations can present unique challenges.", "\"As a Data Analyst, I have presented to a wide variety of audiences made up of people with differing backgrounds. The groups ranged in size from one person to 25 people, with the larger ones composed of co-workers from different departments in the company. Most of these presentations were conducted in person, but I have presented a few analyses remotely via video conferencing to smaller audiences. In addition, about one-third of my presentations have had audiences made up of senior managers.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "As a Data Analyst, what skills do you believe are important for working on a team with people with different backgrounds and varying roles and responsibilities?", "answers": ["As a Data Analyst, you will likely have opportunities to work on cross functional teams. Members of these teams have various backgrounds, differing priorities and varied skill sets. Of course, there are general skills that would be helpful in any team environment. However, hiring managers would be interested in skills that may be somewhat unique to a Data Analyst facing a team environment. If possible, think of skills that go beyond basic ones such as communication.", "\"I believe Data Analysts have the somewhat unique challenge of communicating technical and statistical concepts that many others on the team may not understand. So it is important that Data Analysts are able to explain these types of concepts in a way that that is easily understood by everyone. In order to successfully do so, Data Analysts need to have the ability to apply these technical and statistical concepts to the business - specifically to those parts of the business represented on your team. This is possible when Data Analysts are able to have a more holistic view of the company.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "It is likely you will work with stakeholders who may have a limited understanding of data and databases. Describe a time where you found yourself working in a situation such as this - what specific challenges did you face and how did you deal with them?", "answers": ["As with any job, communication is a key skill for Data Analysts. However, communicating with co-workers from different departments takes a different type of skill than communicating with co-workers within your department. It may require using less technical terms and a larger portion of time listening to their questions and concerns, which sometimes requires patience. The experience you share should reflect how you were able to adapt to working with people who may not have spoken your 'language'. Many times this requires you to have the ability to look at a situation from different perspectives and beyond just your own.", "\"I have run into this situation frequently as a Data Analyst. Each situation is similar to others to a certain degree. In most cases, stakeholders want answers to questions that are not available, because of the limitations of the data that is collected or of the database structure. In these situations, I worked with the stakeholder to develop an analysis to answer related questions that may give them an answer as close to what they are looking for as possible. In the process, I tried to offer them a basic understanding of the data available and of the database structures - nothing too detailed as I thought this may confuse them. In the long-term, we developed a project to investigate whether we are able to collect the unavailable data.  This ensured them that I understood their needs and was willing to work hard at trying to get them what they needed.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "What tools/software do you have experience using in each phase of a data analysis project - from cleaning/preparing data to data exploration to final presentation?", "answers": ["Data Analysts should have experience with a variety of tools as they work with the data and build their analyses. Hiring managers will be aware that sometimes one tool may be used for multiple phases. If this is what you have experienced, do not be hesitant to share this. It will highlight your expertise with that particular tool.  If throughout your career you have used multiple tools for a particular phase, communicate that as well because it showcases your breadth of experiences.", "\"Throughout my career as a Data Analyst, I have been fortunate to have opportunities to strengthen my skills using a variety of tools. In the data cleaning or preparation phase, in most cases I have used Microsoft Excel, and depending on the complexities of the datasets, Microsoft Access if the need arises. I have also used these tools for the data exploration phase.  In this phase, there are several other tools I have used to extract learnings from the data including statistical programs such as SAS and SPSS and analytical tools such as Tableau and Cognos Analytics. I have also used Tableau and Power BI to present my findings through data visualizations in a dashboard format. In addition, Excel and PowerPoint are some of the more basic tools I use to build presentations for internal clients.\"", "\"I have been fortunate to work on multiple tools. I have worked on SPSS, Tableau, Power BI, SQL Server, and Python. Most of the time use SQL queries and SSIS package for initial data analysis and cleaning if I am extracting data from database however I use Python pandas module for data cleansing and exploratory data analysis. Then I used either tableau for visualization reports or Power BI for creating dashboards. I also, use PowerPoint presentations which I need to present my analysis to the stakeholders.\"", "Wow! You definitely sound like an expert in this area! You do a great job of explaining what tools and software you use during the various phases of a data analysis project."]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Considering all the phases of data analysis, what tools/software do you feel work the best for you or you feel the most comfortable using and why?", "answers": ["Over a Data Analyst's career, it is likely they have had exposure, training and experiences using different tools, and over time, they begin establishing preferences for specific ones.  However, employees' options for data analysis tools are limited to what the company has already chosen. If you have experience working at different companies, you are more likely to have exposure to a variety of analytical tools. This question is aimed at understanding what types of tools you are comfortable with and not necessarily the number of different tools you have used.", "\"As a Data Analyst, I find basic tools such as Microsoft Excel and Microsoft Access work the best for me. I feel the  most comfortable using these tools, because they are the ones I have the most experience using since most, if not all, companies have them readily available.  Although most consider these tools basic, I believe with the right training and knowledge you can accomplish many things using them.\"", "\"I have been fortunate to work on multiple tools. I have worked on SPSS, Tableau, Power BI, SQL Server, and Python. Most of the time use SQL queries and SSIS package for initial data analysis and cleaning if I am extracting data from database however I use Python pandas module for data cleansing and exploratory data analysis. Then I used either tableau for visualization reports or Power BI for creating dashboards. I also, use PowerPoint presentations which I need to present my analysis to the stakeholders.\"", "It sounds like you have a significant amount of experience in using various tools and programs for data analysis. This question specifically asks which you feel most comfortable using and why. Perhaps considering adding a sentence or two to your response that outlines your favorite tools to use and why you like them the best."]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Talk about your knowledge of statistics and how you have used this knowledge in your analytical projects.", "answers": ["At the minimum, Data Analysts should have knowledge and experience using basic statistics including mean, median and mode and be able to conduct significance testing. A more advanced level of statistics may be required, but this would be specified in the job description. Data Analysts should not only know how to calculate these basic statistics but should also be able to interpret them in relation to the business.", "\"I use statistics on a regular basis as a Data Analyst. For the majority of my work , I calculate basic statistics such as the mean and standard variances. I also conduct significance testing frequently to determine if measurement differences between two populations is statistically significant and worth highlighting for further investigation. In addition, for a few projects I have worked with correlation coefficients to determine the relationship between two variables in a data set.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "What scripting language have you used in your past projects as a Data Analyst? Which are you most confident using?", "answers": ["Many companies work with multiple scripting languages, so knowing more than one is definitely an asset. If you do not have extensive experience programming with the main language used by the company, highlight your eagerness to learn or strengthen your skills with new scripting languages. Many find that, at a general level, their experience with one scripting language helps them learn new ones.", "\"I have primarily used SQL in my projects as a Data Analyst, and therefore am the most comfortable with it. I have had experience executing some basic Python commands and have made it a goal of mine to receive additional training for it. I have found that my extensive SQL experience has helped me learn Python more easily.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "There are many analytical tools Data Analysts can include in their toolbox. Excel continues to be a common tool for many. Which Excel functions do you have experience using? Describe in detail how you used Excel for one of your analytical projects.", "answers": ["If you are an Excel expert, it would be difficult to list all the functions you have experience using. Instead, concentrate on highlighting the more difficult ones, particularly statistical functions.  If you have experience utilizing the more challenging functions, hiring managers will presume you have experience using the more basic ones. Be sure to highlight your pivot table skills, as well as your ability to create graphs in Excel.  If you have not attained these skills yet, it is worthwhile to invest in training to learn them.", "\"As a Data Analyst, I have used Excel almost on a daily basis. It has become an essential tool for me in all phases of my analytical projects. I have used Pivot tables to check and clean data sets, as well as analyze them. In the analysis phase, I have also used statistical functions to calculate standard deviations, correlation coefficients, percentiles and quartiles. In addition, I have used the graphing function in Excel to develop visual summaries of the data. As an example, I regularly worked on customer satisfaction surveys and received raw data from external vendors. I would take this data and bring it into Excel and use sort functions and pivot tables to verify the data was clean and loaded correctly. As part of the analysis phase, I always worked with pivot tables to segment the data. In addition, if the analysis called for it, I used the statistical functions I mentioned earlier. Building tables and graphs in Excel allowed me to tie my analyses together in visually. Many times, I could complete the tasks in one file, making everything I worked on easily accessible.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Why do you think creativity is a good skill for a Data Analyst to have and how have you used it in your career?", "answers": ["When considering Data Analysts' skills, creativity is not top of mind for many. Instead, plenty of people would consider technical and math or statistical skills to be at the top of the list. However, Data Analysts use their creativity in a variety of ways including developing analytical plans, finding solutions to data issues and presenting data visually. Creativity is about 'thinking outside the box'. Be prepared to share in more detail how you used your creativity for a specific project.", "\"As a Data Analyst, there is no question that creativity is an important skill to have. Creativity is what has gotten me past the data roadblocks in past projects. It has also helped me find new and interesting ways to present analytical results to clients. More specifically, I find that creativity is important when validating data before analyzing it. There have been a few times when I began analyzing data only to find there were some 'abnormal' results. I stepped back and created new and 'non-routine' data checks in order to identify issues causing the atypical results.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "What experience, if any, do you have with web analytics? If you have experience, what tools have you used?", "answers": ["An increasing number of Data Analyst job postings include web analytics experience as a preferred or required skills. At times, companies may choose to separate the roles, but in many cases, they would prefer Data Analysts to have a holistic view, and therefore, choose to integrate web analytics into their job description. When sharing your web analytics experience, give some detail on the types of measurements you were tracking and the general scope of the project.", "\"Using Google Analytics, I have used web analytics as part of a larger marketing campaign evaluation project. The web metrics I tracked included open rate, click-through rate, average time on page and conversion rate. In addition, I was able to build funnels within Google Analytics to measure where visitors were dropping off before converting.  By tracking these web metrics in conjunction with non-web marketing efforts, I was able to recommend the best marketing channels to use to target specific segments.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "How would you rate your writing skills, and in what ways do you use this form of communication as a Data Analyst?", "answers": ["Although Data Analysts spend much of their time working with numbers, having strong writing skills is very important as well. They will need to interpret the results of their analyses into words to present to stakeholders. Data Analysts should be able to tell the 'story' with words and numbers together. If you find that you have not had many opportunities to use or strengthen your writing skills, state the extra measures you are willing to take to change that, whether it be through training or by proactively seeking opportunities.", "\"I have a high level of confidence in my writing skills. As a Data Analyst, I surprisingly have had many opportunities to strengthen these skills. Whether it is through email communications with team members or more formal analytical summaries, I find that I am able to get my point across in a clear and concise manner. I continually look for ways to exercise and strengthen my writing skills.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "In your opinion, what soft skills do you believe to be most important in your role as a Data Analyst and why?", "answers": ["Soft skills are personal attributes that help people work well with others and perform their jobs at a high level. Many refer to these skills as 'non-tangible' and 'non-technical'. As with most jobs, it is important that Data Analysts have strong soft skills, because they do not work in isolation, and therefore their work habits and performance affect others on their team. Interviewers want to know that you understand the importance of these types of skills. Use your past work experiences to support why you find a particular soft skill important and try to include how you have developed it over time.", "\"Personally, as a Data Analyst, I have found leadership skills to be one of the most important soft skills. In my experience, exercising leadership skills does not require you to be in a managerial role.  In a team environment, leadership skills are displayed when you take initiative to guide and help others. In many cases, Data Analysts are in a position where they need to educate others on the data and how to interpret it. I have found it has been crucial for me to speak up and become an expert in interpreting the company data.  Being able to take the initiative has become easier for me over time. I have been able to strengthen this skill by educating myself and finding more opportunities to share my learnings with my team. As a result, I became more confident and built myself up as a leader in this area amongst my team members.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Describe a project where you used both quantitative and qualitative data to conduct your analysis.", "answers": ["Data Analysts should use all the data available to them to conduct the most impactful analyses. This could include both quantitative and qualitative data. The hiring manager wants to know how much experience you may have marrying qualitative to quantitative data. Sometimes it is straightforward, as is the case when working with survey data that has both qualitative and quantitative questions. Other times, it may take some creativity to find applicable qualitative data to use in conjunction with your quantitative data. If you have several projects to choose from, share about the project where you used the most creativity in merging the two types of data.", "\"If possible, I always try to incorporate qualitative data to support what the quantitative data is telling me. I have been fortunate enough to have conducted several analyses where qualitative survey data was readily available to me. However, when working with survey data, I don't think you should limit yourself to the qualitative data from one survey. When appropriate, I have found that there can be valuable qualitative data from other surveys or external sources. For one particular marketing analysis dealing with a new product evaluation, I reached out to the operations department to utilize qualitative data they had collected from distributors. Using this qualitative data strengthened the validity of my recommendations to the product development group.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Describe your experience creating dashboards. If you have experience, what tools have you used to create them?", "answers": ["Dashboards are snapshots of Key Performance Indicators (KPI's) and metrics. Managers and their teams use them to track a particular business objective or goal. With the input of others, Data analysts are often asked to build and update dashboards. There are several tools that can be used to build dashboards including Tableau, Power BI and even Excel. In addition to these well-known tools, there are many free tools available online. If you do not have experience building dashboards, talk about how your data visualization skills can help you in this area. Do not get too detailed describing your experience, but include the purpose of the dashboard, types of data visualizations you used and a few metrics that were included. If the interviewer would like more detail, he/she will ask additional questions.", "\"I have experience creating dashboards that included Marketing metrics. The metrics included brand awareness, customer satisfaction and sales by quarter. I used pie charts, bar and line graphs, as well as tables to present the data in the dashboard. I have created dashboards using both Power BI and Excel.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Which, if any, certifications have you earned related to your career as a Data Analyst?", "answers": ["Hiring managers will be interested in training you have received related to your job as a Data Analyst. Certifications ensure that you have attained a level of achievement set by industries or specific vendors. It provides a form of measurement for hiring managers to assess skills or knowledge of a particular subject or tool. While answering this question, briefly explain how the certifications you have earned have helped you in your career as a Data Analyst. If you have yet to earn any certifications, consider mentioning which ones you may be interested in pursuing in the future and why.", "\"Based on my skills, experiences and education, I have earned the designation of a Certified Analytics Professional. Earning this designation also required me to take a certification exam that measured my knowledge in the field of Data Analytics. I take a recertification exam every three years to ensure that my skills and knowledge are up to date. The requirements of this certification drive me to advance my analytics education and equip me with a stronger toolset to execute my job as a Data Analyst.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Can you describe to me the largest data set you have had to work with from a past project? Tell me how many rows/entries and columns/variables the data set included and details on what kind of data was included - financial, marketing, operational, etc.?", "answers": ["Many hiring managers look for Data Analysts who have the capability to deal with massive data sets with a considerable number of variables and rows. This question is relatively straightforward and you should not feel compelled to review details about the background of the project and any processes you might have gone through. With questions like this, they are interested in the size and type of data.", "\"The largest data set I have worked with was built for a corporate strategy project that required the combined efforts of various departments. This data set had over a million records and 500-600 variables. Included in this data set were Marketing and Operational data that  was eventually loaded into an analytical tool for exploratory analysis.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Describe to me an analysis project you have worked on where the results were the most surprising to you and/or those involved in the project.", "answers": ["When  launching an analysis, most analysts have a prediction on the outcome based on learnings from past projects. However, there will likely be times when the results were unexpected. Your answer to this question will give the interviewer a glimpse of not only the type of analytical projects you have worked on, but also your enthusiasm for them.  When describing your project, be sure to show some passion about the learnings you drew from it. Also consider including what action was taken by you and/or stakeholders as a result of the unexpected results.", "\" In my experience working with customer profiling projects, analyses usually do not show notably surprising results, particularly for established brands.  However, while conducting one routine analysis, I was able to identify a customer subsegment that had the potential to provide additional value to the company if it was offered the right product and services with a relevant message. For me, it felt as if I struck gold - the opportunity to add value to a subset of an existing customer base through new products and services was invaluable.  It was surprising to everyone involved that we could identify a subsegment from this customer base. From there we began strategizing with Product Development and Brand Managers to develop a plan for this new subsegment.\"", "\"In one of my data analysis projects where I worked on medical insurance. I performed the linear regression analysis and one of the insight was the southeastern part of United States pay a lot more premiums as compared to other areas of the United States. And the price of medical insurance premium increase by $350 if you smoke as compared to nonsmokers.\"", "Those are definitely some interesting results! Consider adding some more details about why these results surprised you and/or any reasons you or team members found for the higher premiums. The more information you can provide, the more memorable your answer will be to the interviewer."]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Do you have any experience working with statistical models? If so, please describe in as much detail as possible, the statistical model you worked on and your role in creating it or using it to answer a business question.", "answers": ["Not all Data Analysts will have experience working with statistical models. Interviewers, in most cases, will only be asking this question if statistical modeling was included in the job description. In the case where you are surprised by this question, be upfront about your experience. If you have not had any direct involvement with statistical modeling work, attempt to highlight what you know about it and any training or exposure you may have had to it. Remember, statistical modeling work can include tasks such as building, using or maintaining it.", "\"Working as a Data Analyst, I have had experience working with Statisticians to help them build their models. Although I do not have direct experience building the model itself, I have aided them by analyzing data and ensuring they have access to the appropriate data. The model was built to help the sales team identify customers who were most likely to purchase additional products and services and when they would be most apt to make that decision. This model increased the sales team's efficiency so that time wasn't wasted with customers who were unlikely to purchase again in the near future. I aided in identifying the appropriate variables used in the model as well as evaluating the efficacy of the model upon completion.\"", "\"Statistical modeling is the process of applying statistical analysis to a dataset. A statistical model is a mathematical representation (or mathematical model) of observed data. I had worked on the Regression model which is a supervised statistical model. To be more specific I use a multivariate linear regression model in two projects :\r\n1.\tPredicting the insurance premium to be paid by the customer based on factors such as age, no. of dependents, the region where they live, BMI, gender, smokes and do not smoke, etc.\r\n2.\tPrediction of the pricing of Boston real estate.\"", "So it sounds like you have substantial experience in working with statistical models, which is great! You might want to expand on exactly what your role was in creating the models (e.g., did you work on a team or independently?) and what business questions you were trying to answer. The more details you can offer, the better! Please see below.", "\"Throughout the past several years, I have gained significant experience in working with statistical models. As you know, statistical modeling refers to the process of applying statistical analysis to a dataset and a statistical model itself is a mathematical representation or model of the observed data. I have become proficient in this type of modeling, and, in fact, within my last role, I helped create a multivariate linear regression model for two different projects. In the first case, my team and I used statistical modeling to predict the insurance premium to be paid by customers depending on their age, the number of dependants, location, BMI, gender, and whether they smoked or not. In the second case, we used the modeling to help predict the pricing of Boston real estate. In both cases, the statistical modeling provided us with predictions that greatly benefited the company.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Most large companies house their data in multiple data warehouses. Thinking of one of your more complex analytical projects, how many data warehouses did you have to query in order to gather all the data required?", "answers": ["The technical complexity of your work as a Data Analyst may vary depending on the size of the companies you have worked at in the past. Strong technical skills is an important attribute of a Data Analyst's background. Having experience retrieving data from multiple data warehouses demonstrates your understanding of databases, data structures and programming languages.", "\"In the larger companies I have worked at as a Data Analyst, I have had to work with multiple data warehouses to retrieve the appropriate data. For a particular corporate-wide initiative, I queried against 4 different data warehouses. Once I retrieved the records and variables I needed, I built one large dataset I worked off of to complete my analysis.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Querying, cleaning/preparing, analyzing, and presenting/communicating findings - these are some of the main steps in a data analysis project. Of those I just listed, which ONE step do you enjoy completing the most?", "answers": ["It is acceptable to prefer completing one task over another. However, in many cases, it would be expected that you have experience performing all these types of tasks. Avoid showing aversion to any of the steps in the process. When indicating which step you enjoy performing the most, including an explanation as to why it's your favorite. This may illustrate your strengths to the interviewer.", "\"If I had to select one step as a favorite, it would be analyzing the data.  I enjoy developing a variety of hypotheses and searching for evidence to support or refute them.  Sometimes, while following my analytical plan, I have stumbled upon interesting and unexpected learnings from the data.  I believe there is always something to be learned from the data, whether big or small, that will help me in future analytical projects.\"", "\"As a Data analyst, I always pay extra attention and time while I perform data cleaning and data preparation because it is the basis on which a success and fruits analysis can happen. As it is said \" Good data, good result. Garbage data, Garbage result\". Having said that, I enjoy the data visualization and presentation part because it tells the story hidden in the data and what we worked for.\"", "Excellent response! It's great that you understand the importance of cleansing data since this step is so vital when it comes to producing accurate results. The interviewer will also appreciate that you enjoy the data visualization and presentation part of the process as well. Nice job!"]}, {"topic": "Data+Analyst", "question": "Describe a project where the stakeholders' question couldn't be answered due to data limitations. What advice, if any, did you give to the stakeholders?", "answers": ["At some point, Data Analysts will run into data obstacles when conducting analytical projects. Hiring managers want to know how you would deal with these type of situations, particularly when working directly with stakeholders who may not have a strong understanding of the data. Your answer to this question will also reflect your ability to problem solve.", "\"Years ago, I worked at a company where the executives wanted to initiate a customer segmentation project. However, the data collected in the customer data warehouse was not robust enough to create a meaningful customer segmentation plan. Understanding the importance of this project to the stakeholders, I was able to work with the data warehouse team to outline a handful of data initiatives that would move us closer to a customer segmentation plan.  By the time I moved on from this company, the initiatives were progressing well towards its ultimate goal.\"", "\"It is very normal in the data analysis projects where stakeholders' questions could not be answered due to data limitations, in that can I would sit with the stakeholders and try to understand why they are asking those questions and if there is any other way to answer that question or answer close enough with the data we have and I would initiate a project where we collect the data what could be used to answer that question going forward.\"", "This is a strong response. The interviewer will appreciate that you mention sitting down with stakeholders to listen to and understand their concerns, in addition to doing your best to provide an accurate response with the information you have. Following up to then collect the missing data so that you can fully answer their questions is also great. Excellent! If you have a real-life example you can also provide here, that would help to personalize your answer even more."]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "Describe any metrics you may have created or used as a Data Architect in order to measure quality and consistency of new and existing data.", "answers": ["Having a protocol to ensure data quality and consistency is an important component to any company's data infrastructure. Your experience in this area is valuable as it proves your are knowledgeable about assessing the value of the data.", "\"In my career as a Data Architect, ensuring data quality has always been a part of my job to some degree. There were a number of dimensions we monitored to validate the data quality and consistency. These dimensions included Duplication and Completeness. Duplication measured the percent of records that were duplicated in a given data set, while Completeness measured the proportion of records that had all the necessary data fields populated. By monitoring these particular dimensions we could be alerted to data inconsistencies that could negatively affect the work of data analysts in the company.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "In order to effectively manage a company's data infrastructure as a Data Architect, it is important to have a solid understanding of the business and its strategic challenges. What steps have you taken in past positions as a Data Architect to ensure that", "answers": ["As a Data Architect, you can easily get lost in the technical details of your job while losing sight of the bigger picture of the business. Hiring managers would like to know that you proactively take steps to not lose sight of the overall strategy of the business, since ultimately, this will help you be more effective as a Data Architect.", "\"As I deal with different groups with different needs as a Data Architect, I fully appreciate how important it is to understand the overall strategy of the company. I have been fortunate enough to have employers who continuously communicate the company's short and long-term strategies. If any of the aspects are unclear to me, I make it a priority to attend additional internal corporate training or direct questions to the appropriate people.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "Data Architects take ownership of a company's data infrastructure and may lead teams to build data/database strategies. What challenges have you faced leading teams tasked with data/database strategy development? Describe how you overcame the challenges.", "answers": ["Any team environment can provide challenges whether it is a technical or a non-technical team.  Your answer to this question may be more general and similar to issues many other teams face or specific to those facing technical teams. The main point to communicate is how you handled and overcame the challenges  you faced. If you have not led a team tasked with this, talk about any challenges you may have faced working on this as a team and how the team overcame them. This will illustrate your exposure to these types of situations.", "\"During my career as a Data Architect, I have participated actively on teams where we were tasked with developing short and long-term changes to the database systems in our company. As in many team environments, members come in with different experiences and viewpoints, and therefore have differing priorities. I have found that it becomes a challenge when team members are not open minded and willing to compromise. When team members share well-researched thoughts and evidence and have the willingness to learn, coming to a consensus on next steps becomes much easier.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "Data accessibility and data security is a balancing act for Data Architects. Have you ever had to deny data access to a group/individual in the company? What factors contributed to that decision and how did you communicate your decision?", "answers": ["At times, ensuring both data security and data accessibility puts Data Architects in difficult situations. Employees usually want to be granted access to as much data as possible, but security issues prevent Data Architects from allowing that in the best interest of the company overall. Unfortunately, Data Architects are sometimes put in the difficult position of denying or limiting access to data which, at times, is met with disgruntled reactions. Dealing with people in difficult and uncomfortable situations becomes a valuable skill for Data Architects to have.", "\"There have been many situations where I have had to deny direct access to data. If given the opportunity, people would gladly accept access to all the company data. However, it is not wise to grant open access like that as it compromises the security of the entire corporate data system. In addition, we have found that employees will misinterpret data that they are not familiar with, negatively impacting analyses conducted. In many of the companies I have worked with, we have implemented some requirements that must be fulfilled before data access is granted. The most important part of it is education. Employees must go through specific training to get data access. If there is data that we still are unable to grant them direct access to, we offer our services to work closely with them to get the information they need with our help.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "A company's data needs are constantly changing and improving maintenance and accessibility of data is an ongoing process. Describe a time when you made changes to a company's data management systems and the impact the change made on the company overall.", "answers": ["Inevitably, companies' data needs will change and hiring managers would like to understand how well you adapt to these types of changes. Even more so, they are interested in hearing about how you may have taken the initiative to implement these improvements. If you are earlier in your career as a Data Architect and you have not yet had the opportunity to initiate or be a part of any changes, share how you would have improved the data management systems at your company and what impact those improvements would have had.", "\"While working for one of my first employers, I was part of an initiative to make data more accessible to the company overall. Each department's data was siloed and inaccessible to team members in other departments. Obtaining data outside one's own department was a long and tedious process that prevented the completion of timely analyses. I actively contributed to a project that made data sharing possible without data security being compromised. As a result, analysts were able to complete their projects in a timely manner using a robust dataset. This allowed senior management to make well-informed strategic decisions quickly.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "Have you been involved with the improvement of a company's existing data architecture? If so, explain your role in the process and the impact the change had on the company overall.", "answers": ["Although it is important to complete routine tasks and maintenance, it is also vital for Data Architects to be viewing current environments with a critical eye. Hiring managers would like to hear how prospective hires took the initiative to question current processes and structures with the purpose of increasing efficiency and productivity. Present yourself as someone that continually views the 'big picture' and does not get absorbed in only the routine tasks.", "\"In my experience, marrying external data with internal data within corporate systems can bring about possible issues of data integrity. I initiated a project where I developed a process that carefully screened our 3rd-party purchased data using several detailed steps. I also established a close relationship with our data supplier who agreed to run several checks on the data before sending it over to us. This increased our data reliability and reduced database errors by 34% over a span of a year.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "What kind of challenges have you faced as a Data Architect with regards to security and ensuring the integrity of a company's data is not compromised?", "answers": ["Data security should be a priority for all company employees regardless of their job title or the department they work in. Because of its high importance, hiring managers would like to understand your experience with data security issues. As you answer this question, reinforce that, although your background is not concentrated in data security, you understand its importance in your role as a Data Architect.", "\"At times, it can be difficult to come to a consensus on what should be deemed a security risk. There was an instance where some team members wanted to make changes to the process we used to upload franchisee data to our system. I believed these changes would create security risks, and to support my theory, I quantified the cost to the company if security was compromised. This information helped the team members view the situation from a different perspective and they revised their plan to reinforce data security measures.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "What challenges have you faced working with others in your company who may not have a technical background? How did you overcome these challenges?", "answers": ["It is understood that, in order to make a positive impact on a company overall, Data Architects cannot remain in their own bubble. Undoubtedly, you have had experience working with different departments across the companies at which you have worked. Moreover, it is likely that you have worked with several people who are less technically inclined. Interviewers want to hear how you interact with these people and, in doing so, what challenges you faced. If you have difficulty thinking of specific challenges, consider what helped you avoid them.", "\"I have found that to be a successful Data Engineer you have to understand the needs of the company overall. This has required me to work outside of my comfort zone with others who do not fully understand my role and responsibilities. In addition, because they many did not have a technical background, they did not fully understand the limitations of our data systems. Therefore, I received many requests for deliverables that were not possible to produce which led to much frustration on their part. Overcoming these challenges was not an effortless process. After much planning, we agreed to invest in time to learn about each other's work, and thereby gained a better understanding of needs and limitations. This led to productive brainstorming sessions that produced a variety of possible solutions that we could test. Overall, I believe remaining open-minded and being willing to take the extra step to educate myself and others helped me to overcome this challenge.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "Many companies' data originate from both internal and external sources. Have you faced any obstacles in the past when trying to integrate a new external data source into the existing infrastructure? If so, how did you overcome these obstacles?", "answers": ["Bringing external data into a company's data systems can present challenges as the data may be coming from a source using different systems and data formats. Data architects and their colleagues must ensure that the data is in a format that is readable and useful before it is stored in the company's data warehouse. Hiring managers would like to see that you have problems solving skills specific to external data integration.", "\"In my experience, external data integration issues have usually stemmed from differing systems that created data in a format different from that of our company data. It would be ideal if we could all have the same systems to avoid this issue, but that was cost prohibitive. Instead, I created a script that ran before the data was uploaded to our data warehouse tables. This script changed the format of the external data and ran tests to ensure that it was in a format compatible with our systems.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "As a Data Architect, it's important to stay well-informed on new developments and technologies. How do you keep yourself abreast of the newest industry developments related to data architecture and data analysis?", "answers": ["While working in a corporate environment, employees in technical fields may need to proactively seek out information on industry trends and new technologies. It is relatively easy to get consumed with the work in your company's current environment, while missing out on the changing industry trends. When answering this question, include industry news resources you may subscribe to or conferences and training sessions you may attend on a somewhat regular basis. Hiring managers will likely appreciate that you set aside time from your work schedule to educate yourself.", "\"I do my best to set aside some time in my work week to learn about new trends and technology in the industry. In doing so, I learn things that may be applicable to my job or the company overall. I subscribe to news feeds including InfoWorld and Computer Weekly. In addition, if my schedule and budgets allow, I attend two conferences  per year where I can network with others in my field and attend training seminars.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "An important part of your role as Data Architect will be to understand how the company's stored data is being used across the different departments. What steps have you take in past positions to understand the data needs across these various users?", "answers": ["Because most departments across a company have data needs, it is vital that Data Architects have the ability to work with people with varying backgrounds to understand how they use data. Interviewers want to know what steps you have taken in the past to educate yourself on how different groups use the data available to them. This is important as this information will help you do a better job serving the company's data requirements.", "\"In my role as a Data Architect, I understand the importance of learning about the work completed by different departments in the company and ultimately recognizing each of their data needs. As my schedule would allow, I attempted to meet with the groups on a regular basis to learn about current projects and plan for what their immediate and future data needs might be. Sometimes team members from other groups may approach me proactively with data questions or needs. When this occurred, I asked a plethora of questions to verify I understood the work and needs of their group. I have found it helpful to inquire and never assume when dealing with projects I am less familiar with.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "What is your experience with open source technology? What challenges have you faced using it?", "answers": ["If interviewers ask this question, the company either currently utilizes open source technology or is considering it for the future. If you do have experience using it, mention the specific ones you have worked with. In addition, be sure to also indicate if you have experience modifying the open source programming code. In the event you have not personally faced challenges using it, mention any potential cons you know of to using open source technology.", "\"My experience using open source technology has been positive. I have used both MySQL and Hadoop without facing major challenges. However, I understand that using open source technology can have some general disadvantages including the lack of formal user support, as sometimes you have to rely on advice from user forums to address any issues you may have. Also, in most cases, open source developers don't put a lot of resources into the user interface, so some may find it difficult to learn how to use it.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "What modeling tools do you have experience using? Of these, which do you find the most useful or powerful?", "answers": ["Data Architects should have a solid understanding of data modeling whether or not it is one of their main responsibilities. If you do not have experience using modeling tools, indicate the ones you are aware of and which you know to be the most useful.  Interviewers will appreciate that you have at least a basic knowledge of modeling tools.", "\"My experience with data modeling tools has been primarily with Oracle SQL Developer Data Modeler.  I also have had very limited exposure to PowerDesigner. I found Oracle Data Modeler to be more than sufficient for my needs with its forward and reverse engineering capabilities. However, I have learned that PowerDesigner offers valuable features such as the ability to support a substantial metadata repository and a variety of output formats. One of the more valuable features seems to be the ability to use different modelling techniques that are targeted to different audiences. Of the two tools, I believe PowerDesigner is worth a try for its abundant features and user friendliness.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Architect", "question": "Explain in detail your experience with batch and real-time data processing.", "answers": ["Each of these data processing methods provide distinct advantages and disadvantages and both could be used within a company depending on the business case. If you have experience with one and not the other, give examples of cases where the other processing method would be better suited. This will indicate your familiarity with both types.", "\"I have had exposure to both types of data processing, but am more familiar with batch processing. My experience includes writing programs to process billing data. I wrote programs that captured,  processed and produced output for our billing department. Although my company did utilize real-time processing, I have had less experience with it. I understand the value of it when dealing with our stores' POS systems as it allows for immediate action on the data collected.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "Are you comfortable with travelling for work?", "answers": ["Always ensure to review the job posting before the interview to familiarize yourself with the travel requirements. \n\r\nShould an interviewer ask such a question, it is highly likely you will have to travel. As such, the interviewer will expect you to have applied for the position after carefully reading it, in turn expecting you to be able to travel as needed.\n\r\nShould these requirements be mentioned on the job posting and should you answer in the negative, you may be immediately disqualified. Not only would you not meet a crucial requirement for the role, this would also show you did not carefully read the job posting before applying and the interviewer may think you simply applied to get any job - and as such, you are not serious about working for this employer specifically and/or will not commit.", "\"I carefully reviewed the job posting before this interview and am aware of the travel requirements. I am willing to travel as required.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "Why do you enjoy sifting through data?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to ensure you have good data collection skills and that you can remain motivated. Answer this question by providing an example of such skills in another position as for employers, past behavior is a good predictor of future behavior. Add the reasons why you enjoy the data collection process to demonstrate you will remain motivated to do the work.", "\"I thoroughly enjoy sifting through data because (X reasons, such as considering data as pieces of a larger puzzle, and so on). I pride myself on my excellent data collection skills. For instance, in my last role at (X company), I regularly had to sift through data in my position of (X position title). I (.... X further information re: projects or duties successfully undertaken involving significant data collection). \""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "How do you remain focused while working on tedious tasks?", "answers": ["Answer by providing tools that help you remain focused. Alternatively, mention tricks that you have to keep your concentration.", "\"I always remain focused when working on tasks. I am extremely passionate about the work and love to completely immerse myself and know all there is to know about specific data and records. I have no problem keeping my concentration for a long period of time.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "Why do you think you will excel as a Data Collector?", "answers": ["Answer by emphasizing your greatest strengths against the advertised position. What do you pride yourself on the most? Which strengths will be, in your opinion, most beneficial to this role? Which will contribute to the company's success? Which strengths make you indispensable?", "\"I am a hard worker who does not hesitate to go above and beyond to ensure successful completion of projects, and I am more than willing to take on duties beyond my original job scope. I sincerely believe the company's success is my success. I furthermore meet the required professional and educational qualifications for this role.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "Tell me about your technical skills, including the programs and systems in which you are proficient.", "answers": ["Always do your due diligence beforehand by reviewing the job posting, company website and social media pages to familiarize yourself with the work involved. If technical skills are a requirements, including proficiency in specific programs and/or systems, they are likely to already be outlined on the job posting. \n\r\nIf you applied for this role, the interviewer assumes you already know about these requirements, that you are already proficient and/or that you are currently studying for these programs and/or (i.e., studies in progress).", "\"I am proficient in (X programs and/or systems, including some mentioned as requirements on the job posting, if you are proficient). I am also currently studying for (X programs/systems). I additionally read on your posting that you require knowledge of (X program/system); I am not yet proficient but am absolutely willing to study for it).\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "Why do you want to work for us?", "answers": ["Answer this question by telling the interviewer what seems great about the company, e.g., their services, initiatives, growth opportunities, and so on. Make sure to answer by providing evidence that you did your due diligence before the interview (e.g., by mentioning something exciting you saw on the job posting, company website or social media pages), which demonstrates you are serious about working for this employer specifically and are not simply looking for any job. Link this evidence to your professional goals proving this position was made for you and it is one in which you will excel. \n\r\nFor instance, you can point to their seemingly friendly company culture as per some specific programs or initiatives you came across on their website, and say how friendly and how much of a team-player you are - and that this is exactly the type of work environment you are looking for.", "\"I saw on your website that your company is participating in (X initiative). This is a great initiative contributing to the company morale by strengthening relationships while giving back to the community. I also always seek the opportunity to develop my team playing skills and hope to work with colleagues I will consider family.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "Do you prefer working independently or collaboratively?", "answers": ["Ensure to review the job posting before the interview to familiarize yourself with the work involved. At the time of the interview, you should know whether this position mostly entails independent or collaborative work. As such, should the position entails independent work, you should answer this question by saying you prefer independent work. Should the position entails collaborative work, you should answer this question by saying you prefer collaborative work. \n\r\nShould you not answer adequately as per the duties involved, you may be automatically disqualified - for instance, if you answer you prefer collaborative work and dislike independent work when applying for a position that mostly entails independent duties. Not only will this show you are unsuitable for this position as you did not do your due diligence beforehand (as you did not read the job posting before applying for the position (nor before the interview)), but the interviewer may also believe you are simply looking for any job without being serious about working for this company particularly.", "\"I pride myself on my team playing skills as I sincerely enjoy working with others toward a common goal. However, I prefer working independently as it is easier for me to allocate my time and resources.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "What do you look forward to the most in this position?", "answers": ["Always review the job description before an interview. Answer this question by mentioning one or some of the duties you look forward to the most by selecting one or several duties from the job posting. Thereafter, link this preference - or these preferences - to your own experience in a similar capacity, where applicable, to demonstrate you already possess the required experience for this role.", "\"I look forward to (X data collection duty listed on the job posting) as I have extensive experience in that area. For instance, while employed for (X company) as (X position title), I (X further information proving your successful experience and matching this particular duty).\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "How would your references describe you?", "answers": ["Answer this question by mentioning how respectful, reliable, and how much of a hard warder you are, notwithstanding any challenges you may face.", "\"My references would say that I am a hard worker who thrives on challenges and who works tireless to meet deadlines. They would also say that I am a committed and reliable individual who remains highly respectful and professional at all times.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "Why did you decide to pursue a career as a Data Collector?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer what motivated you to pursue this career and apply for this position specifically. Answer this question by mentioning, e.g., how passionate you are about this field and why.", "\"I decided to pursue a career as a Data Collector because I (X reasons, such as having a passion for this career and/or a parent in this role). Furthermore, as I am highly meticulous and detail-oriented, I know I am in the right field.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "What modules have you created for data collection?", "answers": ["Review the job posting and company website/social media pages before the interview to familiarize yourself with the modules you will have to create in this role, or modules the company has created or will soon be creating. \n\r\nAnswer by providing examples included on the posting or company website/social media pages, including your own experience in similar roles, if you have any. Alternatively mention some of the modules listed on the job posting or company website/social media pages are modules you look forward to creating and why, to demonstrate a motivation to undertake training despite not currently having the required experience for this role.", "\"The modules I have created are (X modules listed on the job posting or company website). For instance, in my last position as (X position title) for (X company), I (... detailed information regarding the modules created, which have contributed to the successful completion of projects).\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "What do you know about our company?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your knowledge of the company you applied for. It is imperative to always conduct your due diligence before an interview by reviewing the job description, company website and social media pages to familiarize yourself with the company and work involved. \n\r\nIt is also important to show the interviewer you did not apply to the advertised position simply because you are looking for just any job, but that you wish to work for this company specifically.", "\"I reviewed the job description and website before this interview and know you are a company specializing in (X programs/services you noticed on the company website). I am particularly excited about (X programs/initiatives) that I saw on your (website/social media pages) as I (X reasons you are excited about these programs/initiatives, such as passion or similar initiatives undertaken in school or volunteer capacity).\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "How would your current or former employer describe your work ethics?", "answers": ["Employers are looking for commitment, reliability, respect and professionalism. As such, answer this question by including how committed, reliable, respectful and professional you are, notwithstanding the challenges you may face.", "\"My supervisor would describe my work ethic as excellent. I am a hard worker who thrives on challenges and who works tireless to get the job done. I am also a committed and reliable individual who remains highly respectful and professional at all times.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "Why should we hire you?", "answers": ["Answer by emphasizing your greatest strengths against the advertised position. What do you pride yourself on the most? Which strengths will be, in your opinion, most beneficial to this role? Which will contribute to the company's success? Which strengths make you indispensable?", "\"I am a hard worker who does not hesitate to go above and beyond to ensure successful completion of projects, and I am more than willing to take on duties beyond my original job scope. The company's success is my success. I furthermore meet the educational and professionals requirements for this role.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "Tell me about your organizational skills.", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your organizational and time management skills in a work environment by providing an example of your capabilities.", "\"I believe excellent organizational skills are essential to successfully perform in a work environment. For example, I use a strategic approach by anticipating, and keeping track of, all upcoming calls, meetings, and deadlines. I will use lists to keep track of upcoming duties and a calendar to keep track of upcoming events. I also keep a record of all documentation and update on a regular basis to ensure the most up-to-date information is easily accessible, enabling me to be prepared should unanticipated events occur.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "What attracts you to the research we are conducting?", "answers": ["Answer the interviewer by pointing out to the research that the company is conducting. Always do your due diligence before your interview to prove you know the company you are applying for and that you are really looking for employment with this company specifically, i.e., that you are not simply looking for any job.", "\"I saw on your website that your research involves (X). This is extremely exciting and in line with what I studied in university (...) (X example of research conducted in university and why such research was so exciting). The conduct of this type of research is one of the reasons why I applied for this position at your company, and why I believe I am the perfect fit.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "When have you been most surprised by the results of any study you have participated in?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your data collection experience related to a surprising study you participated in, and why the results were surprising to you. If you do not have such experience, tell the interviewer about any study you participated in, in a university setting or volunteer capacity. Alternatively, mention the studies that you hope to participate in, as per, e.g., the studies outlined on the company website.", "\"The study I was the most surprised by was (X study). I participated in this study while working for (X company) as a/an (X position title). It was a very surprising study because (X results and why this study particularly surprised you, e.g., results were against all odds, and so on).\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "Tell me about your background and how it relates to this field.", "answers": ["Provide an overview of your professional experience while putting emphasis on your data collection experience as per the advertised position, proving you indeed have the qualifications required for this position. \n\r\nReview the job description before your interview and answer this question by selecting some of the main duties on the posting and telling the interviewer you have performed these duties in the past, when and how.", "\"I pursued a Bachelor's degree in X at UCLA and upon graduation I worked as an Intern for [X company] where I was responsible for [X data collection duties ]. Since this internship, I have gained considerable data collection experience working for [X company] where I managed [X data collection duties] and for [X company] where I was responsible for [X data collection duties]. These are some of the reasons I believe I am a perfect fit for your position.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "How would you describe your meticulous skills?", "answers": ["Should such a question be asked, it is highly likely that meticulousness will be particularly important in the work that you will be performing for this employer. This is why you should always ensure to review the job posting before the interview to familiarize yourself with the day-to-day work involved. Such question would be expected if you are adequately prepared for the interview. Answer this question by providing an example of your excellent meticulous skills.", "\"I pride myself on my excellent meticulous skills. For instance, (X example of your excellent meticulous skills, e.g., when working on a team project in a professional or volunteer capacity, or in a university setting, and how your skills contributed to the project's success).\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Collection", "question": "What motivates you in your career?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your passion for this career, what motivates you to be the best in your field, and what you look forward to the most in this position. \n\r\nReview the job posting and company website before your interview to familiarize yourself with the company and duties involved, and mention one or many duties that you look the most forward to (related to your motivation), and why. This will show the interviewer that you are passionate about your work and that you also did your due diligence before your interview.", "\"What motivates me the most is becoming the best in my field, and as a result having the opportunity to make an impact on a greater scale and contribute to the company's long-term success. For instance, with this position, what motivates me the most  is the opportunity to (X newly acquired duties that will enable you to help the company be more successful, as per the job posting).\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Do you prefer  work in more of  a Generalist role or concentrate your work on the Pipeline or  Database?", "answers": ["Data Engineers may have not have a choice to the type of role they play. Much of it depends on the size and type of company at which they work. Generalists tend to be more highly skilled as they are responsible for a larger variety of data tasks. Those whose work is concentrated with the Pipeline tend to work more closely with Data Scientists and are more familiar with getting the data prepared for analysis. Data Scientists whose work is concentrated on databases may work more with the ETL process and table schemas. As you answer this question, be sure to include all your experiences (if you have worked in more than one type of role) and why you prefer one type over another.", "\"With the majority of my work experiences as a Data Engineer, I worked in more of a Generalist role. I prefer this over the other two types, because I enjoy having knowledge of the entire structure and process.  I have received training on a variety of topics relevant to Data Engineers and enjoy utilizing all of my attained skills, if possible, instead of concentrating on a subset of them.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Data Engineers work closely with Data Architects. How do you see your job differing from that of a Data Architect?", "answers": ["In asking this question, the interviewer is likely trying to gauge your understanding of different roles  within a data warehouse team (or the department in the company responsible for maintaining the databases). There is no 'right' answer to this question as the roles and responsibilities of Data Engineers and Data Architects differ from one company to another and may also have some overlap.", "\"In my experience, the difference between the two roles have varied depending on the organization. People in the two roles work closely together, but I believe have some general differences in their responsibilities. A Data Architect builds the data architecture for the organization's data systems and manages the servers. He/she maintains a holistic view of how the data moves into and throughout the organization. Data Engineers also may have a role in the building of the architecture, but in my experience his/her role is concentrated more on the testing and maintenance of it. In addition, the Data Engineer ensures high quality and reliable data is available to analysts in other parts of the organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Do you have experience introducing new data analytics applications? If so, what obstacles did you run into while introducing and implementing them?", "answers": ["Introducing new data analytics applications within a company does not happen frequently, because it's cost prohibitive. However, when companies do roll out new data analytics tools, it can become quite a production as the tool has to be connected to the company's current systems, training has to be administered to relevant users, and regular maintenance of the tool needs to be managed. If you have never had experience introducing a new data analytics application, be sure to explain what you know about the process of doing so. This will let the interviewer know that, when the situation arises, you will have some foundational knowledge to help you through the process. If your experience ran smoothly, point out what possible scenarios may have presented themselves as obstacles and how you may have handled them.", "\"In my last position as a Data Engineer, I took part in the roll-out of a new data analytics application in my company. Introducing new applications takes careful planning to attempt a smooth transition to the new tool. With my experience, I found that even with careful planning, unforeseen circumstances can occur. In the early stages of the tool's introduction, we had unexpected high demand for user licenses. This required reallocation of resources to purchase additional licenses as well as reprioritization of training schedules to meet the needs of different departments. We also had to ensure that our infrastructure could support the significantly higher number of employees utilizing the tool.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Do you have experience training others on thing such as software, applications, porcesses or architecture? If so, what have you found to be the most difficult aspect of doing so?", "answers": ["Training may be one of a Data Engineers many responsibilities. Co-workers may need to be trained on new processes or systems you have built  or new employees may need training on well established architectures and pipelines. Technology is constantly changing so it is likely training opportunities will exist on a regular basis. When identifying the difficult aspect of training you experienced, be sure to also include how you dealt with it.", "\"Yes, I do have experience administering both individual and group training.  Through my experiences I have found that one of the more difficult aspects is training new, but experience employees, who have come from a company that approached data from an entirely different perspective. These new employees may 'speak the language' and have the necessary skills, but sometimes have strong opinions on how to approach different projects.  It becomes a challenge to train them when they struggle to be open-minded. I have learned  it is helpful to highlight the successes we've had with our processes and architecture to help them realize there is never a 'one-size-fits-all' solution.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Are you comfortable working 'behind the scenes'? Alternatively, are you comfortable coming out and being in the 'spotlight'?", "answers": ["Compared to Data Scientists, Data Engineers tend to work 'behind-the-scenes' since their work is completed much earlier in the data analysis project timeline. Decision makers in the company aren't always interested in how the data is made available. Instead, they are usually more interested understanding the learnings Data Scientists glean from the data using their statistical and machine learning models. Your answer to this question will reveal a bit about your personality - whether you only thrive in the 'spotlight' or are you able to work in both types of situations?", "\"As a Data Engineer, I am used to working 'behind the scenes'. What's more important to me than being in the 'spotlight' is being an expert in my field and having a positive impact on the company through my work. I take pride in the work that I do and how I can set the company up for success. However, I do not shy away from the 'spotlight' when necessary. If there is an issue within my department that requires attention from my manager and/or company executives, such as the need for additional resources, I do not avoid bringing attention to it for the good of our team's work and ultimately the company.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Describe a time when you found a new use for existing data that had a positive impact on the business.", "answers": ["As a Data Engineer, you may be one of the few who have a bird's eye view of the data throughout a company. In many situations, departments work with a specific set of tables within the corporate databases and therefore may unknowingly be limiting their analyses. To add the most value to the company's strategies, it is valuable, at a general level, to know the initiatives of each department. This gives Data Engineers the ability to provide valuable insight into what data is available and beneficial for analyses being conducted throughout the company.", "\"As a Data Engineer, I try to take time to understand the strategic initiatives being conducted across the company. I believe departments need to avoid working in silos and should have approved access to data owned by other groups within the company. From my perspective as a Data Engineer, I was able to connect employee data with sales data to better understand the reasons behind both high and low sales periods. Upon further analysis, it was revealed that hiring employees with a particular education and work experience profile resulted in significant increases in sales for an extended period of time. Prior to this discovery, human resource data was never used in conjunction with sales data for analyses.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Have you ever been in a data disaster recovery situation? If so, describe the situation and your role.", "answers": ["Beyond the completion of daily assignments, hiring managers are looking for Data Engineers who can quickly contribute to the remediation of emergency situations. When a data infrastructure fails and/or data becomes inaccessible, lost or destroyed, it can have damaging effects on the company's operations. Companies want to ensure that they are ready with the right resources to deal with these unfortunate events if they occur. In many cases, it becomes an 'all hands on deck' circumstance.", "\"In my most recent position, I was part of the group charged with developing a Disaster Recovery Plan. Therefore, I was familiar with what needed to take place when a data disaster recovery situation actually occurred. A corrupt file was somehow loaded into our system and caused databases to lock up and much of the data to become corrupted as well. I was responsible for working with our IT team to ensure that our data backups were ready to be loaded and that users throughout the company continued to have connectivity to the data they needed.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Which programming/scripting languages do you have experience utilizing? Which one do you have the MOST experience with?", "answers": ["In most cases, job descriptions will outline which programming language skills are preferred or required for the job, so going into the interview you should have this information if it was made available to  you.  Specify which language you have the most experience with, but circle back to the preferred/required programming language(s) if you have used it/them in past projects so you at least let the interviewer know you have had some exposure to it.\n\nIf you do not have experience with it/those, the hiring manager must have found other valuable aspects of your resume that would be beneficial to the job. If this is the case for you, concentrate your answer on the language you have the most experience with and highlight any similarities it may have to the required or preferred language. In addition, highlight any strengths you may have with learning new concepts or languages. You want to convey to the interviewer that you will be dedicated to working with the systems and programs that the  company has in place, even if it requires additional training.", "\"I have experience programming with both Python and R, but most of my work has been done using Python. I understand the job summary specified that R is preferred, so I want to assure you that I firmly believe I can strengthen my R programming skills  quickly while working on the job. I tend to pick up concepts quickly and learn the best while performing tasks.\"", "\"The languages I have had the most exposure to are SQL, Java, R and Python. I am most comfortable using SQL since this is the language I have used most often in various school class projects.  However, I enjoy expanding my programming knowledge base by learning new languages. I realize that sometimes one programming language may not be the best solution in every scenario.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Which ETL tools do you have experience utilizing? Do you prefer one over the others? If so, why?", "answers": ["In the process of answering this question, the interviewer should be reassured that you are familiar and have experience with the ETL process. Therefore, after you list the ETL tools with which you have experience and declare your preferred one, be sure your reasons for your preference reflect your knowledge of the ETL process.", "\"I have experience using both PowerCenter and Oracle Warehouse Builder, but based on my experiences, prefer PowerCenter. I have found that, relative to other ETL tools, the advantages to using PowerCenter include: a single point of control which strengthened security, universal connectivity that allowed for data access and integration from several different sources and scalability that kept us ready for future increases in data needs.\"", "\"Through my college coursework, I have been exposed to a variety of ETL tools and have experience with some of them including SAP Data Services, IBM Infosphere and SAS Data Management. Based on this experience and various industry articles I have read, I found Informatica's PowerCenter to be the most effective ETL tool because it provides  a high level of flexibility when it comes to changes in the business and has also been known for its high performance rate. Flexibility and high performance rates are important attributes of an ETL tool as it guarantees that, despite changes in the business or its structure, its data operations will continue to run smoothly with the data remaining accessible.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Do you have experience building data systems using the Hadoop framework? If so, explain a particular project in detail.", "answers": ["Hadoop is one of many tools a hiring manager may specifically inquire about. Being asked about your experience with a specific tool or language is most likely an indication that it is something used on the job. Prepare for the interview by researching which languages and tools they use at the hiring organization. In most cases, this would be outlined in the job description. If you have little or no experience with the specified tools or languages, conduct research to at least show you have some knowledge of them. If you do have experience with the tool, make sure the explanation of your project reflects your knowledge of its capabilities.", "\"Yes, I have had experience utilizing the Hadoop framework on a project where my team was tasked with increasing data processing efficiency. The Hadoop framework was implemented to increase data processing speeds without compromising quality through its distributed processing. Hadoop was also chosen for its scalability as our organization anticipated our data processing needs would increase significantly in the near future. This project had limited resources so Hadoop was an attractive choice because it has a open-source framework. It is also Java-based which reduced the training required as most of our team was familiar with the language.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Do you have extensive experience working in a cloud computing environment? What benefits and challenges do you see working in one?", "answers": ["It is well known in the industry that there are benefits and challenges to cloud computing.  Whether or not you have experience working in a cloud computing environment, it is important to convey your understanding of the benefits and challenges. It reflects your understanding of current issues and technology in the industry. In addition, if the company you are applying to does  utilize a cloud computing environment, at the very least, they will be assured that you are aware of possible issues that may arise from it.", "\"The prior companies I have worked for did not utilize a cloud computing environment. However, I am aware that many people feel that working in this type of environment may compromise data security and privacy since data is not kept within the walls of the company.  In addition, you have limited control as the infrastructure is controlled by the service provider. However, benefits likely would include cost savings and more reliability as downtimes would be minimal since most service providers grant agreements guaranteeing a high level of service availability.  In my opinion, whether cloud computing is right for a specific company would highly depend on the structure of its IT department and the resources available to it.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "What is your experience level with NoSQL databases? Give me an example of a project/situation where you found building a NoSQL database to be more appropriate than a relational database.", "answers": ["There are advantages and disadvantages of using one type of database over another. In your answer, try to communicate what you know about each and through your example show how you would apply your knowledge to an actual project.", "\"Modeling a database in NoSQL can be advantageous in some situations. One situation in particular was when the franchisee system in our company was increasing in size exponentially. We needed the ability to scale up quickly so we could take advantage of all the sales and operational data now available to us. Scaling out, as opposed to scaling up with bigger servers, is the way to go when dealing with increases in data processing loads and this is more easily accomplished through NoSQL databases. Scaling out can be more affordable and can be accomplished more efficiently than scaling up. NoSQL databases also have the ability to handle larger volumes of data, which is important when you need to react quickly to significant changes in data loads in the future. There are certainly more developers familiar with relational databases versus NoSQL databases, but the extra training is well worth the benefits in my opinion. In addition, although relational databases may have more connectivity to analytics tools, I believe the future is bright for NoSQL databases in this regard as more analytics tools are being developed.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Do you have experience with data modeling? If so, what data modeling tools do you have experience using?", "answers": ["As a Data Engineer, you likely have some experience data modeling- defining the data requirements required to support your company's data needs. Besides mentioning the tools you have used for this task, include what you know about data modeling on a general level and possibly what advantages and/or disadvantages you see in using the particular tool(s).", "\"Although I have worked in some companies where I was not highly involved with the data modeling process, I make it a goal to keep myself familiarized with the data models in the company. This always gives me a better understanding of the entire system. However, I have worked at some companies where I was more involved in the data modeling process and had the opportunity to utilize the tools available. I have experience using Oracle SQL Developer Data Modeler which allows us to create, browse and edit a variety of data models, and I found the ability to forward and reverse engineer very helpful as well. This tool helped us develop conceptual models as we work with business stakeholders, and also logical data models where we can define data models, structures and relationships in the database.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Data maintenance is one of the many responsibilities of a Data Engineer. In many cases, tasks related to this are fairly routine. Describe a time when you encountered a data maintenance problem that required you to deviate from your \"routine\".", "answers": ["Data maintenance usually occurs on a set schedule with a specified task list. With a good data maintenance strategy, these tasks tend not to change often which is a good sign - that means everything is operating as expected. Inevitably, there will be something unexpected that occurs that may throw things off and require extra attention. The interviewer would like to see that you have experience dealing with unexpected situations like these.", "\"As routine as data maintenance may become, it's alway important to keep a close eye on all the tasks involved, including ensuring that scripts are executing successfully. One of the data maintenance tasks involved conducting an integrity check. This allowed us to ensure our systems were not corrupted. After conducting this check, I was able to locate a corrupt index that may have caused larger issues in the future. Because of this discovery, I decided to implement an additional maintenance task as a extra safety precaution to help prevent corrupt indexes from being added to our databases.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Do you have experience building custom analytics applications? If so, please describe the application you created.", "answers": ["Building custom analytics applications requires Data Engineers to not only know the data well, but also to understand the analytic needs of the different groups across the company. They must work closely with these analysts to plan and build these custom applications. So, in addition to having the programming skills, it is important to have good communication and teamwork skills.", "\"The Marketing department was looking to marry its primary Marketing Research data with sales data stored in our corporate databases. The custom application I built, allowed them to conduct ad hoc analyses quickly, which in turn helped them react quickly to the competitive environment. The application allowed them to avoid the traditionally long process of requesting data from the data warehouse and loading it into Excel or Access.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "What kind of experience have you had working with Data Scientists and what skills do you have in common with them?", "answers": ["Some working in the industry may think that Data Engineers and Data Scientists have some overlap in skills and possibly responsibilities. At the minimum, Data Engineers should have a general understanding of what type of projects Data Scientists work on. At a high level, the two positions differ in that Data Engineers deal with the maintenance, architecture and overall preparation of data for analytical purposes, while Data Scientist create use statistical and machine learning methods to glean learning from the data.  As Data Scientists rely heavily on the work of Data Engineers, hiring managers may want to understand how you have interacted with them in the past and how well you understand their skills and work.", "\"In most of my positions, I have had the opportunity to work with Data Scientists. I met with many of them on a regular basis to better understand their roles and to aid them with their projects. I found that it was not difficult to work with them, because we both understood analytics and were trained in some of the same programming languages. Having these overlapping skills allowed me to more easily understand the Data Scientist's data needs, while she understood the limitations of our infrastructure and the data available. \""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Which certifications have you earned that are applicable to your job as a Data Engineer? Which was your most recent one and when did you earn it?", "answers": ["Certifications serve as proof that you received formal training for a skill and not did not just learn it on the job. The number of certifications may also be indicative of your dedication to increasing your knowledge and skill base. Technology in this area is always changing and keeping your skills up to date is vital, so recency of training and certifications could likely be taken into account. If you haven't had the opportunity to work towards any certifications, mention what training you receive on a regular basis to ensure you are up to date on all the technological advancements in your field.", "\"Over the past few years, I have become IBM Certified as a Data Engineer and also received professional certification through Google. I regularly look for training classes that will broaden my skill set and knowledge and also attend various Big Data conferences throughout the year. I am currently working towards a Microsoft Professional certification in Data Engineering with Azure.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Outside of your technical skills, what skills do you find most valuable as a Data Engineer? These could be skills you attained from jobs unrelated to data.", "answers": ["Career-specific skills are important to have, but there are many atypical skills that are necessary to be a successful Data Engineer. When answering this question, try to 'think outside the box', and avoid answers such as Communication or Teamwork skills.", "\"Over the years, multitasking and prioritizing have become invaluable skills for me. I began strengthening these skills in a job unrelated to Data Engineering. As an administrative assistant working with a department of a dozen people, I had to learn to prioritize tasks and complete some of the simultaneously. This has become a skill I use frequently as a Data Engineer since I work with many different departments in the company. In any given week, I'm approached by different departments with several different data requests. I have to manage these requests by prioritizing their needs, and in order to get the requests fulfilled efficiently, I use my multi-tasking skills.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Some in the Big Data industry consider  Data Engineering to be a non-analytic career path. Do you agree or disagree with that statement and why?", "answers": ["There can be a couple of different ways to interpret this statement. Yes, relative to other Big Data career paths, Data Engineers may not use their analytical skills as frequently as a Data Analyst. Therefore, relative to other career paths, Data Engineering may be considered non-analytic. However, this does not mean that Data Engineers do not use analytical skills at all.  Hiring managers would like to know how you view a Data Engineer's role versus that of others in the company working with data. Express your understanding of a Data Engineer's role and how analytics is part of the required skill set. Cite at least one example of how you may have used analytics in your past roles as a Data Engineer.", "\"I would have to disagree with this statement as I have used analytical skills frequently as a Data Engineer. Whether conducting analyses to ensure data quality and integrity or evaluating new service providers or hardware, my analytical skills have been crucial to my performance on the job. In addition, my analytical skills have help me when working with Data Scientists and Analysts on various projects. They help me better understand the data they need for their projects.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "If you had the time and resources, what types of training courses would you enroll in to help you in your job as a Data Engineer?", "answers": ["With technology constantly changing, most ambitious Data Engineers could easily rattle off several training courses they would enroll in if they only had the time in their busy schedules. The answer to this question may not only reflect where your interests lie, but it can also be an indication of your perceived weaknesses. Find a way to offset any possible interpretations of weakness by mentioning strengths you have in related skills.", "\"I find it very important to keep up with advancements in my industry, so I believe enrolling in training courses on a regular basis should be a high priority for Data Engineers. At this time, I would choose to enroll in training courses related to ETL processes and the cloud environment. In current and past roles as a Data Engineer, we are always looking for ways to improve our processes to become more reliable and efficient. I have been fortunate enough to work in teams where our architecture and processes ran relatively smoothly and efficiently. However, it is always important to continuously evaluate  your current situation and be proactive about finding ways to improve.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "What led you to a career in Data Engineering?", "answers": ["Some arrived to the Data Engineering field along a very traditional path - earning a degree in a related area (Computer Science, Information Systems, Data Science, etc.) and working at data-related jobs along the way. Others may have started on an entirely unrelated career path and made the switch to Data Engineering. Either way, the answer to this question reveals more about your education and experiences and the decisions you made along the way. Do not be hesitant to share your background and experiences if you did not arrive to this field the traditional way. Instead, touch upon what general skills you may have attained while earning your degree and working at your other jobs.", "\"As long as I can remember, I have always had an interest in computers. Once I reached high school, I knew I wanted to pursue a degree in Computer Engineering.  While in college, I began to realize that I enjoyed my math and statistics courses almost as much as my computer courses. Upon graduation, my first job was a Data Analyst position for a large financial services company. I found great satisfaction in using my math and statistical skills, but missed using more of my programming and data management skills. Through some associates in my company, I learned about the Data Engineering field and started taking courses to learn more about it. I found it to be the perfect combination of my interests and skills. Fortunately, within a year, a Data Engineering position opened up in my company and I was able to make the switch without a problem.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "What do you find to be the most difficult aspect of being a Data Engineer?", "answers": ["Reasonable hiring managers will understand that people run across difficult aspects of their job all the time. Avoid glossing over this question in fear of highlighting  a weakness. Instead identify something you have may have struggled with and add how you dealt with it.", "\"One difficult aspect of being an Data Engineer is managing the sometimes conflicting demands of different departments within the company. Balancing the needs of the different departments with the capabilities of our infrastructure is one the biggest challenges I deal with on a regular basis. Although it has been difficult, I always try to see the positive aspect of the situation. Dealing with these conflicting demands has required me to learn more about the work of all of these departments.  It gives me an invaluable holistic view of the company and allows me to see how all the 'pieces' fit together. So, in a way, I feel fortunate to have this challenge as there are only a few others who are exposed to this view of the company.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Give an example of when you proposed changes to improve data reliability and quality. Did these changes end up being implemented? If not, why not?", "answers": ["Continuous improvement of the current environment is something hiring managers value. It is even more advantageous for you if these proposed changes were self-initiated and were not an assigned task, so be sure to highlight this if that is the case.  This will display your ability to 'think outside the box' and the priority you place on quality of the company's work overall. If you have never had an opportunity to propose changes to improve data reliability and quality, explain why you think it's important and what you would do as a Data Engineer to ensure the data quality was always at a high level. In addition, if your proposed changes were not implemented for reasons such as lack of time or resources, go ahead and state that, but make sure you emphasize your continued commitment to finding new ways to improve data quality.", "\"While working in previous positions related to data,  data quality and reliability were always things I considered as high priorities in my projects. While working on one particular project, I noticed there were several discrepancies and outliers in the data being stored in the company's database.  After identifying several examples of this, I built a case to develop a data quality process into our department's routine. This included conducting a weekly meeting with representatives from different departments within the company to identify and troubleshoot data issues. Although this took time away from other projects, everyone felt it was well worth it, and in the long run, saved us from dealing with larger problems that would've been more costly for the company.\"", "\"I believe that the work I produce is only as good as the data or evidence I have to back it up. That's why it is important as a Data Engineer to continuously ensure that the data your company collects and relies on to make strategic decisions is clean and of high quality.  If not, I need to help identify the issues and possible solutions to improve the data. As I work on any project, I am continually evaluating whether there is a more efficient or effective process to accomplish the task at hand.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Describe a project you worked on where you played an active role in solving a business problem through the innovative use of existing data.", "answers": ["'Innovative' and 'active' are the key words in this interview question. Hiring managers would like to see that you are vocal and actively contribute your ideas and experience to a project. If possible think of an example where you may have initiated or took charge of a project. It will be important to emphasize your role in coming up with the innovative solution to the problem and to not spend too much time explaining the problem itself.", "\"While working for one of my previous employers, I was engaged in an initiative aimed at identifying the cause of the company's high employee turnover rate.  By examining data from other areas of the company including Marketing, Finance and Operations, I identified key areas that required further examination. I found the data in these areas of the company had some high correlations with employee turnover rates. I worked with the analysts in these departments to better understand these correlations. This led to strategic changes within these departments that had a positive effect on the employee turnover rate.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Engineer", "question": "Working with data can present a variety of challenges. Can you think of a time where you ran into an unexpected challenge bringing together data from different sources? How did you end up overcoming this challenge?", "answers": ["Your answer to this question should showcase your problem-solving skills and how you react to unexpected challenges. The interviewer may ask for a situation related to your previous experience working with data, as  specified in the question listed, or may leave it as more of a general question about dealing with challenges. If you have not experienced the specific situation, think of how you would approach the challenge if you encountered it in the future.", "\"While working in my previous positions, my teams and I have always strived to anticipate data issues that may occur during the ETL process. However, inevitably, an unforeseen issue or circumstance will arise. In particular, I worked for a company that included a franchise system that required data to be collected from a variety of locations and systems. One of the franchisees changed his system without notice which created loading issues for his store's data. I worked to develop a short-term solution to get the crucial data into our system for corporate-wide reporting and also began developing a long-term solution to avoid similar situations in the future. \""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "What is meant by the term \"snapshots\" as it relates to data migration?", "answers": ["The interviewer is continuing to ask technical questions about various terms and aspects of a data migration system. As mentioned earlier, the majority of this interview will involve either operational or technical questions.  Preparing for the interview should include reviewing a glossary of terms used in the data migration practice.", "\"Snapshots are copies of read-only data which is stored in a master table.  The primary use of a snapshot is to maintain a copy of the master table at a remote site so that it can either be accessed quickly or replicated if needed.\"", "\"Snapshots are a copy of the master data table which are stored remotely.  They are only as current as when they were recorded and are only updated when a subsequent snapshot is made.  Snapshots are typically used as a backup to the master table or to provide remote users with faster access to the data.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "What are some of the standard data formats in a data migration system?", "answers": ["This is an example of a technical question.  Technical questions usually ask for definitions or brief explanations of the topic about which the interviewer is asking.  Technical questions are best answered directly and succinctly, with little embellishment.  The interviewer will ask follow-up questions if they need additional information.", "\"There are various standard formats in a data migration system. These include flat files, XML datasets, independent DBMS working tables, normalized entity/relationship schemas, and dimensional data models.\"", "\"Most data that can work with a wide variety of data formats.  This is important because administrators may not know where the data will be extracted from when designing the system or may not be familiar with the data formats in the source databases., Data formats most systems can manage include flat files, virtually any DBMS system, normalized entity/relationship schemas, XML datasets, and dimensional data models.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "Can you name some of the popular data migration tools available to database administrators?", "answers": ["By asking this question, the interviewer is seeking to understand what tools you are familiar with and whether the tools you use are the same ones they are currently using.  Keep in mind that they may also be interested in whether you can bring new tools into their organization.  Again, having done your research, you should be familiar with what they already use and can structure your answer to either match their tools or suggest new ones.", "\"There are several excellent data migration tools currently available. The ones I prefer include Oracle warehouse builder, SAP data services, IBM infosphere information server, and SAS data management.  These address my needs and integrate well with the systems I typically use.\"", "\"Choosing a data migration tool depends on several factors.  These include the environment, the data sources, the data warehouse, and the platforms you are using. The tools I like include Power center Informatica, Elixir repertoire for data migration, data migrator (IBI), and SQL Server integration services (SSIS.) These cover 90% of my needs, are flexible, and are easy to work with.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "Can you discuss partitioning in data migration, including the types of partitions and what benefits they bring to data migration?", "answers": ["You'll note that this question has three parts.  The interviewer is asking you a general question about partitions, and specific questions about the types of partitions and their benefits.  During an interview, you need to listen to the questions you are being asked carefully.  Make sure you reply to each part of the question providing all the information about which the interviewer is asking.  Interviewers will note when you don't do this.", "\"Partitioning in the practice of data migration is the sub-division of transactions.  The two types of partitions in data migration are round-robin and hash partitions.  Partitions are used to improve the performance of the data migration process.\"", "\"Partitions are a crucial tool used in the data migration process. Partitions involve sub-dividing transactions.  The two main types of partitions are round-robin and hash.  The benefit partitioning provides is to improve the performance of a data migration transaction.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "Can you tell me the names of the three layers in a data migration system?", "answers": ["This is a follow-up question to the one the interviewer previously asked, and you responded to.  Follow-up questions are common during an interview, especially when the interviewer has a particular interest in a topic or is looking to solicit more information from you based on the answer you already provided.  You should be prepared for follow-up questions throughout the interview.", "\"There are three layers and a data migration system.  The first is the source layer which is the layer where the data first lands. The next layer is the integration layer, where the data is stored after it has been cleansed. The third and final layer is the dimension layer, where the presentation layer stands.\"", "\"Data migration systems have three distinct layers.  The first of these is the source layer, which obtains the data from external sources.  The middle layer is where the data is transformed and screened to ensure it is appropriate for the data warehouse.  The final layer is the dimension or presentation layer.  This is where users access the data for various purposes.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "Why is it important to have real-time data migration into a data warehouse?", "answers": ["This question is meant to explore your understanding of the link between data migration and the business objectives of the organization.  The data migration in itself is only as useful as the information it provides to the organization to run the business.  Understanding the link between these two processes is critical.  The interviewer is seeking to confirm that you are aware of this.", "\"The purpose of a data warehouse is to provide useful information to the business and its decision-makers.  Real-time data migration into the warehouse enables the decision-makers to have the latest data with which to manage the business.  This is especially important for companies that use OLTP, such as retailers or financial firms.\"", "\"Real-time data migration is one of the more critical functions of a data migration team.  Businesses depend on usable data to make decisions and operate the company.  Having real-time data provides decision-makers with the most up to date information.  This is particularly important in businesses that operate in dynamic industries in which conditions are continually changing.  It is also essential for companies that execute real-time transactions, including retailers and financial firms.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "Can you explain the key features of a data migration system within a data warehouse?", "answers": ["This is a general or opening question.  An interviewer will ask this type of question early in the interview to get you talking, to learn more about you, and to extract information they can use for subsequent questions.  You can use this type of question to begin to steer the interview in a direction in which you are comfortable discussing.  \n\nFor exampl: \"The data migration system, which is also known as the Extract-Transform-Load (ETL) system, is the foundation of a data warehouse. A properly designed data migration system retrieves data from a variety of sources, scans and confirms the data and enforces data quality and consistency standards, and finally delivers data in a readable format. This enables application developers to use the data to build applications and end-users to use it to make informed decisions.\"", "\"The data migration system, which is also known as the Extract-Transform-Load (ETL) system, is the foundation of a data warehouse. A properly designed data migration system retrieves data from a variety of sources, scans and confirms the data and enforces data quality and consistency standards, and finally delivers data in a readable format. This enables application developers to use the data to build applications and end-users to use it to make informed decisions.\"", "\"Data Migration systems are a critical part of the overall data warehousing plan. Data must be migrated properly for it to be used effectively within the data warehouse.  Key elements of a data migration system include verification, quality checks, standards, and formatting.  If done properly, that data then becomes available to application developers and decision-makers.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "What are the day-to-day functions a data migration system performs?", "answers": ["The interviewer is asking this operational question to understand your knowledge and experience in this field.  Before the interview, you should have done a great deal of research on the company and its operations.  This will allow you to structure your answers to their questions to demonstrate how your skills and experience can help them address their business challenges.  \n\nForexample: \"Data migration systems perform several different functions. This begins with building the development, test, and production suite of the data migration processes. It will then analyze and extract data from the sources identified by the operators. The system also verifies that the data is safe and complies with the standards of the organizations. Next, the data is formatted into dimensional schemas for the most effective delivery to end users, business intelligence tools, data-mining tools, OLAP cubes, and analytic applications. Finally, the system self-checks and can be tuned to optimize the performance of the overall data migration process.\"", "\"Data migration systems perform several different functions. This begins with building the development, test, and production suite of the data migration processes. It will then analyze and extract data from the sources identified by the operators. The system also verifies that the data is safe and complies with the standards of the organizations. Next, the data is formatted into dimensional schemas for the most effective delivery to end users, business intelligence tools, data-mining tools, OLAP cubes, and analytic applications. Finally, the system self-checks and can be tuned to optimize the performance of the overall data migration process.\"", "\"A comprehensive data migration system performs a variety of functions.  Initially, it will create subsystems that allow for the management of the system itself.  It will then seek out external sources of data and began to import information into the data warehouse.  During the import, the data is verified and scrubbed to make sure it is the appropriate information and that there are or no threats embedded within the data.  The system then formats the data so that it can be used in a variety of different ways, including application development, data mining, and extraction for decision-making processes.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "What operations are executed in a data migration system, and in what order?", "answers": ["This is another technical question.  The nuance of this question is that not only is it asking you to define the steps, but also asks what order in which they are performed.  This will ensure that you are knowledgeable about this process and have used it before.", "\"The typical data migration system consists of three distinct operations.  These include extracting the data from the data source, which can be an Oracle, Microsoft, or any other relational database, transforming the data by performing a data cleansing and validation process, and writing the data into the target database or data warehouse.\"", "\"Regardless of which data migration tool you are using to transfer data from the sources into a data warehouse, the operations performed are similar.  The three distinct processes are extracting the data from the source, cleansing or validating it, and then writing it to the target database or data warehouse.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "What is the purpose of data profiling in the data migration system?", "answers": ["This is another operational question by which the interviewer is trying to determine your knowledge of this particular operation within the data migration process.  You should be able to answer these types of questions easily based on your experience in this area.  It is always advisable to brush up on the fundamentals in your field before an interview.", "\"Data profiling is a careful examination of the scope, quality, and content of a data source to enable a data migration system to be built. Its purpose is to verify that the data source has been well maintained before it is migrated to the data warehouse. If done effectively, the data will require minimal transformation and human intervention to load directly into the tables of the data warehouse.\"", "\"Data profiling is the process used to verify that the data being imported into the warehouse is clean, formatted properly, and the correct information the administrator is anticipating.  The purpose of data profiling is to minimize and the edits, data manipulation, or human interaction with the data after it has been migrated into the data warehouse.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "Can you explain what a data migration validator is and how it is used in data migration?", "answers": ["Yet another technical question.  Remember, technical questions ask you to define the specific topic within the field you are interviewing four.  Technical questions are best answered directly and concisely.  You should anticipate follow-up questions which the interviewer will use to extract more information from you.", "\"A data migration validator is a tool used to test the data. I can facilitate the execution of data integration, data warehousing, and data migration projects. It makes uses a specific architecture to extract, load, and validate data from a variety of data sources, including databases, flat files, XML, Hadoop, and Business Intelligence systems.\"", "\"The process of validation within a data migration project is meant to make the extraction of data from a variety of sources and integration of the data into the data warehouse easier and faster.  Its function combines extraction, loading, and validation of the data into a single process.  The data validation tool as agnostic with regard to the type of files it can work with.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "Can you describe the roles and responsibilities of a data migration team?", "answers": ["This is a general question which the interviewer will likely ask early in the process.  Your response will give them some insight into your background and your understanding of both the data migration process and the roles that the administrators play in moving data from one source to another.  You can use general questions to help direct the interviewer in the direction in which you are comfortable discussing.", "\"The primary role of the data migration team is to create and manage the data warehouse.  The responsibilities encompassed in this role include delivering data to end-user tools, performing the cleaning and conforming steps, protecting and documenting the extraction of the data, and ensuring the consistency with the sources of the data.\"", "\"The data migration team has several roles and responsibilities.  Their primary responsibility is to ensure the data is extracted from sources and moved to the database in an efficient and trustworthy manner.  The duties the team performs include extracting data from the original sources, assuring the quality and cleaning the data, applying labels and measures to the data, and delivering the data in a format that can be used by query tools, report writers, and dashboards.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "Why is it important to analyze the impact of changes in a data migration system?", "answers": ["This is another operational question which the interviewer is using to determine the depth of your knowledge in this field.  As the interview progresses, the questions will become more complicated and more specific.  This signals that the interviewer is growing more confident in your abilities and is willing to investigate more complex topics.", "\"Examining the metadata associated with an object determines how it is impacted by a change in its structure or content. Changing data can break processes that are crucial to the function of the data warehouse. Allowing ad-hoc changes to data staging objects could be detrimental. Once a table is created in the staging area, you must perform an impact analysis before any changes are made to it. Many data migration tool vendors provide impact analysis functionality.\"", "\"It is critical to analyze the impact of changes in a data migration system because any change could alter the functionality of the system.  The best way to mitigate the impact of any changes to the system is to analyze them during the staging process.  This will catch any errors or negative impacts before they are implemented when performing the full data migration process.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "What is the best way to process a fixed-length flat file?", "answers": ["The interviewer is asking you this operational question to make sure you know how to perform this process.  Your response should be in the form of a step-by-step description of what you would do to accomplish this task.  You don't need to get too technical or provide too many details.  The interviewer will ask a follow-up question if they need more information.", "\"A fixed-length file layout should include the file name, where the field begins, its length, and its data type, which will usually be text or number.  You only need to supply those layout information once.  The tool will remember this and expect a similar format for subsequent fixed-length flat files.  Data validation is essential in this process in case the format of the data has changed.  The most likely change will occur if the data includes a date field.\"", "\"Fixed-length flat files are simple to process if you first define the layout of the files.  The information included in this definition is usually the beginning of the file, its length, and the data type.  This information is initially entered manually and will remain the same until the data migration tool encounters a file with a different format.  This will cause the migration to fail and alert you that some manual intervention is required.  It is recommended that you perform periodic validation processes to ensure that the data format has not changed.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "What is the difference between an initial load and a full load process in the context of data migration?", "answers": ["By asking this question, the interviewer is testing your knowledge about different terms and processes involved with data migration.  If you are experienced in this field, you should have no problem responding to this question.  Keep your answer brief and allow the interviewer to ask a follow-up question if they need more information.", "\"In the context of data migration, the initial load is the process for populating all data warehousing tables for the first time. Full load also refers to the first time a data warehouse is populated. However, using the full load process, all the records are loaded in one batch after all the contents of the table have been erased.\"", "\"Full load an initial load both refer to populating a data warehouse table for the first time.  The differences with the initial load data is transferred into the data warehouse for the very first time.  The table never contained any data.  In the full load process, the data warehouse table is first erased to remove any data that was previously loaded, and then the new data is populated in a single batch.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "What then is meant by an incremental load?", "answers": ["This is a follow-up to the previous question.  When an interviewer has a particular interest in a topic or wants to dig deeper into your knowledge of the subject, they will ask follow-up questions.  You should be prepared for follow-up questions any time you've provided an answer to the interviewer.", "\"Incremental load refers to applying dynamic changes after the initial or full load process. These are performed as needed or when required in a specific period or on predefined schedules.\"", "\"In incremental load refers to the process of populating the data warehouse tables after the initial load or full load has been performed.  Any subsequent migration of data into the tables is considered an incremental load.  These can be ad hoc or on predefined schedules.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "With regard to data migration, what is referred to as a Three-Tier System?", "answers": ["This is another question that will test your knowledge of data migration and data warehousing.  You can assume the interviewer will have access to a wide range of technical and operational questions they can ask you.  While there is no way you can study and be prepared for every single question, you should be able to handle most of them.  If you're asked a question you can't answer, simply tell the interviewer that you don't have that information handy, and then describe how you would go about locating it.", "\"The data warehouse is the 3-tier system in data migration. The first tier is the end-users or the front end. The middle tier in data migration provides end-users the data that they can use and which is secure. The final tier is the back end, where the data is stored.\"", "\"With regard to data migration, a three-tiered system refers to the data warehouse.  The middle tier serves as the interface to both the users on the front end and the data on the back end.  It is what retrieves the data based on the user quarries and makes it available in a usable and secure format.  The front end is the users, and the back-end is where the data is stored.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "What are views, and how do they differ from materialized views?", "answers": ["In this technical question, you are being asked to define and compare two different but similar terms.  Make sure that you thoroughly answer the interviewer's questions by first providing the definition, and then discussing the differences between the phrases.  You may want all enhance this by also discussing how the terms are used within data migration.", "\"Views are representations of the data that are contained in the table.  Views are created using the attributes of one or more tables. A view of a single table can be updated, but those with multiple tables cannot.  Materialized views are created from an aggregated table which contains data from either fact tables or dimension tables.  Materialized views can be updated.\"", "\"The two main types of views are regular and materialized.  They differ in terms of how the data is obtained and how the view can be updated.  Standard views use data from either a single table or multiple tables.  Single table views can be updated, but multiple fable views cannot.  Materialized views aggregate data from several different tables, including a fact table or dimension table.  Materialized views can be updated through Foot Data has already been aggregated.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "What is a powercenter as it relates to data migration, and what is the difference between a powercenter and a powermart?", "answers": ["This question this summer to the previous one and that it is a technical question asking you to define and compare two similar terms.  You can use the same approach you already employed by first defining the words and then describing the difference between them.", "\"A powercenter is a function within the data migration process which connects with data sources and extracts information from them. The sources are ERP applications, including SAP, Oracle Apps, and PeopleSoft.  Powercenters process large volumes of data, whereas a powermart processes small volumes.\"", "\"The two functions within a data migration system which access data from external sources are called powercenters and powermarts.  Both of these connect with external sources, but only powercenters can connect with ERP systems such as PeopleSoft, Oracle Apps, and SAP.  The difference between a powercenter and a powermart is the volume of data it can handle.  Powercenters handle large volumes, while power marts can only handle small volumes.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "Can you discuss round-robin and hash partitioning in more detail?", "answers": ["You're being asked another follow-up question.  Any time you provide an answer to an interviewer, you can anticipate follow-up questions. This indicates that the interviewer has a particular interest in this topic or needs more information than what you provided in the previous answer.  Noting this will help you anticipate future questions and identify which issues are essential to the organization.  \n\nFor examp: \"In round-robin partitioning, the data is evenly distributed among all partitions. Using round-robin partitioning is appropriate when the number of rows in each of the partitions is the same. Hash partitioning applies a hash function to partition keys to group data among the partitions. The results in a group of rows being processed with the same partitioning key in the same partition.\"", "\"In round-robin partitioning, the data is evenly distributed among all partitions. Using round-robin partitioning is appropriate when the number of rows in each of the partitions is the same. Hash partitioning applies a hash function to partition keys to group data among the partitions. The results in a group of rows being processed with the same partitioning key in the same partition.\"", "\"As mentioned earlier, the two main types of partitions are round-robin and hash partitioning.  Round-robin divides the data equally among the various partitions within a transaction and accelerates the transaction.  Hash partitioning uses partition keys to group data among the partitions.  The transaction is accelerated because rows with the same partitioning key are processed together.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "Can you discuss what is meant by an operational data store and how it works?", "answers": ["An interviewer will ask you this question to continue to probe your knowledge of data migration and learn how you use this particular technique in managing a data warehouse environment.  As the conversation continues, you'll notice links between the questions previously asked and the ones you are being asked currently.  Make sure you are consistent in your answers throughout the interview.", "\"An operational data store or  ODS is where the data is depository between the staging area and the data warehouse.  The ODS acts as a temporary data warehouse allowing operators to analyze the business data before fully populates the tables in the data warehouse.  Data can remain in the ODS anywhere from minutes two weeks, depending on the need for the data and the operational characteristics of the organization.\"", "\"The operational data store or ODS functions like a cache between the staging area for incoming data and tables within the data warehouse.  The ODS provides analyst the opportunity to review the data before is fully accepted into the data warehouse.  Like the data warehouse, the ODS generates primary keys, takes care of any errors in the data, and will reject data that it doesn't need or that have been corrupted.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "How are the tables in data migration analyzed, and when does the analysis occur?", "answers": ["There is another technical question that contains two parts; the first being a how which is a process question the next being a when which is it clarifying question.  You're reminded to answer every part of a question which an interviewer asks, especially with a technically-oriented interview.  Doing this demonstrates both your listening skills as well as your attention to detail.", "\"The tables in a data migration process are analyzed by reviewing the statistics generated using the analyze command.  The same statistics can be used by a cost-based optimizer to create a data retrieval plan.  The analyze statement also supports the creation of the object's structures, space management, and other operations within the data warehouse tables.  The tables are analyzed either when the index table is created or when the cluster is complete.\"", "\"The analyst managing a data migration process use statistics to analyze the tables in the data tables.  They use the analyze command to perform this function.  The information generated by analyze can also help to optimize how the data is retrieved and make the process more effective.  The best time to analyze the tables is when the index table is first created or after the cluster is complete.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "How do you fine-tune the mapping of the data during data migration?", "answers": ["By asking this question, the interviewer is indicating that this topic is important to them.  Hopefully, your pre-interview research helped you to discover this, so you're prepared to address this question.", "\"There are several steps involved in the fine-tuning of the mapping of data during a migration process.  You can use a filter to qualify the data, utilize persistence to create a cache during the lookup operation, aggregate the data, sort it by a group, and use operators' when writing the functions.  Another technique is to increase the cache size and commit intervals.\"", "\"When mapping the data during a data migration, you can fine-tune it to increase the performance and reduce the retrieval time.  Techniques available include filtering, qualifying, used utilizing caches, aggregating the data, sorting it into groups, and utilizing operators within your functional expressions.  You can also increase the cache size and the commit intervals to optimize the mapping process.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "Please define the term workflow and discuss how it is used in the context of data migration?", "answers": ["This is a straightforward question, which by now you should recognize as another technical question.  You should be very adept that answering this type of question at this point in the interview.  Keep your answer concise and to the point, and allow the interviewer to ask a follow-up question if they are more interested in this topic.", "\"Workflow is simply the set of instructions that determines how the tasks are executed during a data migration process.  Defining an effective workflow makes the process more efficient.\"", "\"In the context of a data migration project, the term workflow refers to the progression of tasks that are executed during the data migration.  Creating an efficient workflow expedites the migration process and results in a table within the data warehouse, which is more useful and has greater integrity.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Migration", "question": "Can you explain the differences between a connected and an unconnected lookup and when you should use each of them in a data migration?", "answers": ["This question asks you to compare two similar but different terms and to discuss when to use them in data migration.  This is a typical operational question which starts with a definition and then asks you to describe how you would apply it.  As a seasoned data migration operator, you should be able to answer this question easily.", "\"The two types of lookups are called connected and disconnected.  A connected looked up is used for mapping and will return multiple values.  It is called connected because it can be tied to another transformation.  On the other hand, and unconnected lookup is used when it cannot be connected to another transformation.  It returns a single value, but it is reusable.\"", "\"Connected and unconnected lookups or similar but slightly different.  They both query the tables and provide values as a result of the operation.  The difference is that connected lookups are part of the workflow and can be tied to another transformation.  Unconnected lookups only provide a single output and cannot be connected to other operations.  Both types of lockups can be reused if necessary.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "Describe to me a data project you worked on in the past that you would do differently with the knowledge/experience you have acquired up to this point and/or new technology that was not available at the original time of the project.", "answers": ["This is a Behavioral question, which the interviewer uses to determine how you dealt with a specific issue in the past and how you would deal with it if you encountered it again working for their organization. Behavioral questions are best answered using the STAR format. This stands for Situation, Task, Action, and Results. Using this format helps you organize your answer and lead the interviewer through your story in a systematic manner.", "\"In my current position, we performed analysis on a large set of data to determine why the company didn't achieve the results they expected from a major initiative they had implemented (Situation.) Management had a hypothesis and expected the analysis  to confirm this (Task.) We completed the analysis, but the data led us to reach a different conclusion (Action.)  My colleagues and I repeated the analysis but used a modified data set and different analytical tools, and this time the results matched the original assumptions. However, when management implemented changes based on this study the results were the same as before (Results.) What I learned is to be true to the methodology and let the results speak for themselves o the problem can be accurately identified and addressed.\"", "\"Experience has taught me that as hard as we try, we will still occasionally make mistakes. What's important is turning a failure into a learning opportunity.  I once was assigned a project on which the data set was small and the anticipated results were easy to predict. I opted to utilize a simple approach and manual analysis methods instead of following protocol and using automated tools. I thought this would save time since the outcome was predictable. As I progressed through the analysis, it became apparent that the project was more complex than originally thought and the outcome was not as predictable.  I had to restart the project, losing time and the resources I had already invested in the project. I learned to not cut corners and always follow protocol because eventually, I would have to anyway. \""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "Many companies rely on Data Scientists to tell them what analysis is possible with the data available. Talk about a time when you took the initiative to recommend a new business measure for the company to track.", "answers": ["Data Science by its nature is a disciplined practice with little opportunity for creativity or changes. However, organizations like their employees to be able to take the initiative and innovate to improve processes, with the goal of reducing costs or increasing the outcomes of actions they take. When preparing for an interview, you should have a few stories available which demonstrate initiative and out-of-the-box thinking.", "\"During one of my previous jobs I was on a team which focused on customer satisfaction scores. We determined this by analyzing data involving product returns, repeat purchases. customer referrals and by using text analysis. While performing this work I noticed a correlation between customer satisfaction and a specific feature of one of our products. I knew the feature couldn't be altered, but I thought that if it was highlighted in the product documentation and suggestions for its use emphasized. the customers would use it more often. I recommended this to the product manager who implemented my idea. The result was an increase in the use of the feature and a corresponding reduction in customer complaints.\"", "\"As a Data Scientist, my job is to analyze data sets and report the results. The other company stakeholders use this information to improve products, services, and processes or to make better business decisions. However, I like to look beyond the data and identify trends that are more subjective in nature. An example of this was when I was working on a project involving employee absenteeism at one of the company's manufacturing facilities. The data identified some factors contributing to the absenteeism patterns, but I sensed there was something else not indicated by our analysis. I took the initiative to informally interview a sample set of the employees and found that they had strong opinions about the food served in the cafeteria. I then added this factor to the study and confirmed that increases in absenteeism correlated with specific menu items.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "Can you compare Sas, R and Python programming tools and describe their use in Data Analytics?", "answers": ["This is a Technical Question, which seeks to determine your technical capabilities and your knowledge of common tools used by Data Scientists. By specifying these tools, the interviewer is indicating that these are what their organization uses and expects you to be competent in. You should be able to compare these and state their purpose in analyzing data, even if you don't regularly use them.", "\"Sas, R, and Python are probably the most commonly used tools for data analytics. Sas has a wide array of functions, a user-friendly graphical interface, and strong reporting features. R's strength is that it is an open-sourced tool and is widely used in academic and research environments. Python is also an open-sourced product but is more widely used and supported.  It is easy to learn and interfaces well with other tools. The best part about Python is its large portfolio of libraries and modules.\"", "\"While there are many data analytics tools available, Sas, R and Python are probably the most popular and widely used. Of these, I prefer Python. This is due to its large number of user-created libraries and modules, its ease of use, and its robustness in areas such as statistical operations and model building. R is also open-sourced but is more popular with the academic and scientific community. Sas is by far the most widely used data analytics tool and has an easy-to-use graphic interface and probably the strongest statistical functions. Sas' only drawback is its licensing cost, which can be prohibitive for smaller organizations.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "Describe to me your experience with machine learning methods. Is there a particular method you have more experience with than others?", "answers": ["The purpose of this question is to explore your knowledge and experience with machine learning. The interviewer may want to confirm not only your skills in this area but also your direct knowledge of the machine learning methodologies their company utilizes. Be prepared to provide a concrete example and the rationale behind using the methodologies you chose.", "\"Much of my experience with machine learning is in the area of medical imaging. Our team employed machine learning methodologies including classification, clustering, and regression analysis to help improve the accuracy of the assessment of the images our equipment produced.\"", "\"Since most of my work was focused on filtering spam within the email application we developed, I utilized the Classification methodology of machine learning, specifically the NaiveBayes algorithm.  This allowed us to address the large data set we used for training and the multiple attributes we filtered for. \""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "When your job requires you to be immersed in data, you can discover some interesting patterns or trends. What is the most interesting learning you discovered through the mining/exploration of data?", "answers": ["An interviewer may ask this type of question to learn more about you as a person, vs. exploring your technical skills. People hire people, and one of the main purposes of an interview, besides confirming your qualifications for the job, is to determine if you would be a good fit for the organization. This question will provide some insight into both your personality and your ability to communicate your ideas.", "\"Being immersed in the data is one of my favorite parts of being a Data Scientist. I often discover things I didn't expect or wasn't even looking for. Once, while parsing data to determine how consumers go about shopping for a new car, I discovered that the most important criteria most people used was color. Respondents to the survey we use listed this more often than make, model, features or even price. This enabled the organization to redesign their marketing campaign to emphasize the variety of color options available for their vehicles.\"", "\"While people outside of the field of Data Science believe our profession is dry and mundane, I find it fascinating. It is called \"data mining\" for a reason because buried in the piles of data we examine as part of our job are nuggets of gold.  These are in the form of the results we predicted and are supported by the data, as well as discoveries we didn't expect . An example of this was learning that a process improvement our organization made on it's manufacturing line not only solved the problem it was meant to address but also resulted in fewer defects in the final product. When we explored this in more detail, using data analytics, we discovered that the new process helped operators detect and remediate a chronic issue earlier, thereby eliminating the need for rework. This \"ah-ha moment\" is one of the perks of the job I do.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "What statistical software programs do you have experience using in past positions in this field? Which one do have you the most experience with or feel the most confident using?", "answers": ["This is a technical question, the purpose of which is to determine your familiarity with and knowledge of software used by data scientists. The interviewer is also interested in learning whether you are adept at working with the software and tools their organization utilizes. The best way to answer this question is to first state the names of the software you have used and are familiar with, and then make the point that most statistical analysis software products have similar features and that you've been able to easily transition from one to another one when necessary.", "\"In my current position, we use Tableau for the majority of our work.  We also have licenses for Statgraphics and JMP Statistical Software, but these are only used in circumstances in which their unique features are more suited for the task at hand. I've also used Salesforce Analytics Cloud and MATLAB in previous roles. I've found that transitioning to a new software analytics tool is relatively easy due to the similarity in the features and user interface between the different packages.\"", "\"The primary software tools I use for statistical analysis are Tableau, Statgraphics, and JMP. Each of these performs similar functions, but each also offers unique features that make specific types of analysis easier and more accurate.  My experience has taught me that once you are familiar with the basic functions of statistical analysis software, you can move between different tools by simply learning the user interface and the functions each one offers. I'm curious about which tools your organization prefers and why.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "Data visualization is an important skill that will be used often when communicating results with stakeholders. Describe to me one of your most innovative data visualization ideas that went beyond pie and bar charts.", "answers": ["Data Science and analysis of complex data sets is a very technical discipline. However, the organization's stakeholders who use the results of the analysis need to be able to clearly understand what the data is telling them and be able to use it to improve their operations and help them make business decisions. You need to be able to present your work in a manner that is easy to understand and utilize. This is known as data visualization. The interviewer is seeking to understand how you organize and present the data to accomplish this objective.", "\"While the process of analyzing data is important, it is critical that the results of the analysis be useful to the stakeholders in the organization. It is important to understand what the stakeholder's objectives are when deciding how to present my results. One method I've found to be effective is to add graphs, pictures, and illustrations to my presentations and reports. Once, when presenting an analysis of customer usage trends for a product our organization sold, I incorporated images of the product and animated them to expand in size in relation to the growth in customer adoption, adding the statistics and actual growth numbers. The audience remarked about how clear this made the information.\"", "\"I am always cognizant of how my data analysis will be used by the stakeholders in our organization and seek to present my results in a manner that is relevant to the audience and in terms they can easily understand. I often use visual representations of the data along with the actual numbers to achieve this. Recently, when presenting a study on the implementation of process improvement and the results it generated, I used a photo of the actual production line, and animated it, increasing the speed of the line as the process was improved and the production times were reduced. I included the actual percentages of the time saved above the line so the management team could easily see the results which were achieved.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "What experience do you have conducting text analytics?Describe a project you worked on that required text analytics.", "answers": ["This is another technical question which the interviewer will ask in order to confirm your skills and experience as a Data Scientist. They want to ensure that you are qualified for the job and are familiar with a specific process that they use to analyze data to improve the results of their operations.", "\"Text Analytics is the process of creating meaning out of written communications. A common usage of this is In a customer experience context, examining text that was written by, to, or about customers. This helps find patterns and topics of interest and then enables the organization to take action based on what it learns. While working on a recent project involving the review of a service our organization provides, I examined the email communications between our support team and the customers. My analysis identified a specific issue that customers inquired about frequently. We then reviewed the documentation related to this and realized that it was vague and somewhat confusing.  After updating the information and performing subsequent text analysis, I confirmed that the number of customer inquiries about this issue had dropped by 70%.\"", "\"Text analysis is the process of examining written communications to discover trends or create meaning. It involves sentiment analysis, key phrase extraction, and entity recognition. It usually is used with customer communications to improve a product or service. While working on a recent project to determine which of our company's services customers found the easiest to use, I analyzed email exchanges between the sales team and their customers. The results revealed that while customer surveys indicated that one service was the most popular, the email exchanges found that the customers actually enjoyed using another service more. This enabled the company to adopt some of the features of this service to improve customer satisfaction with the other ones we offered.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "How have past positions unrelated to data analysis helped you in your current profession as a Data Scientist?", "answers": ["The purpose of this question is to gain a broader picture of your background and experience. In addition to being able to perform the tasks related to the job you are interviewing for, organizations prefer to hire individuals who can expand the role of the job to accomplish other organizational objectives. They are also interested in your fit and how you may improve the company culture.", "\"When I was young and still in school, I didn't have the goal of becoming a data scientist. However, I was naturally curious and enjoyed learning new things. I also liked solving problems, especially using numbers and sets of data. One of my first jobs was in a library where I had to reshelve books. I quickly learned that if I spent some time organizing the books before I began replacing them on the shelves, I could reduce the amount of time the job took. I challenged myself to continually beat my previous times by devising new ways to organize the books and navigate through the library. I tracked this and charted my progress. This made a routine job more interesting and enjoyable.\"", "\"Data Science involves identifying an issue, determining a methodology to analyze it, collecting data, performing the analysis and interpreting the results. My first experience with this type of process was while working in a grocery store during high school. My job was to replace items that customers either returned or decided not to purchase while they were checking out. At first, I considered this to be a boring and repetitive job, but then I started to notice patterns in the products I was working with. I began keeping track of the products and looking for patterns. I found that many of the products not purchased or returned by customers were ones that had ambiguous pricing information. I shared my charts and conclusions with the store manager, who agreed with my results and took steps to clarify the pricing information. I continued to track the products and found that the changes we made resulted in fewer returns and non-purchases.\" This sparked my interest in data science and led me to this career.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "Describe a project where you had a surprisingly difficult time dealing with unstructured data. How did you overcome the obstacles and what tools did you use?", "answers": ["By asking this question, the interviewer is revealing that their organization deals with unstructured data and needs to hire someone who has experience with this and can organize this type of data to make it usable. Your answer needs to include a specific example of how you accomplished this in a previous role to prove your ability to do it again.", "\"Unstructured data is difficult, but not impossible to work with while performing an analysis. The key is to utilize tools and techniques designed to effectively analyze this type of data. On a recent project, I was tasked with helping the sales team to improve its customer relationship management process. I utilized a combination of a NoSQL database and Amazon's Simple Storage Service (S3) to collect and analyze the data, producing the results the sales team needed.\"", "\"Unstructured data, also known as Big Data, is the fastest-growing type of data in the industry. This has presented Data Scientists with a challenge when attempting to use this type of data to analyze trends, processes and customer behavior.  I have learned that special techniques and tools are required to incorporate unstructured data into the analysis I'm performing. These include looking for patterns, keywords, and sentiment in textual data, and using natural language processing technology. I recently worked on a project involving employee communications and attempting to improve individual productivity. Using the tools and techniques I previously mentioned, I was able to determine the specific behaviors the most productive employees exhibited. This enabled the management team to train and coach the other employees, thereby improving their productivity.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "Data Scientists do a lot of exploring and testing of hypotheses. Tell me about a time where you were given freedom to explore a business problem with very few parameters. What was your initial approach in attacking this project?", "answers": ["This is another question that is meant to help the interviewer determine your level of creativity and initiative.  These are qualities not typically associated with Data Scientists, but which are key to the results they produce.  Organizations value employees that are willing to work independently with little supervision and are confident enough to be responsible for their actions. The best way to respond to this question is with confidence and a straightforward answer.", "\"One of the most rewarding parts of my job is the ability to work on a project with few parameters and the freedom to explore and experiment. I was recently assigned to determine why sales of one of our products had fallen off. I decided to approach the problem from two perspectives; those of the sales team and the customers.  Using text analysis, data visualization, and other analytical techniques, then comparing the results from the two groups, I determined that the issue was one of communication. I recommended that the sales team modify their messaging and follow up with the customers in a more timely fashion. This helped to reverse the fall-off in sales.\"", "\"Many people believe that Data Scientists are very structured, disciplined individuals with little creativity or imagination. In my experience, just the opposite is true. Successful Data Scientists know that many times the answers they are seeking lay outside of the parameters which define the project they are working on. They realize that they need to be open to exploring new ideas without imposing any restrictions on their thinking or the analysis they perform. While working on a project to help improve the process for onboarding new customers, I was given a set of parameters for the project. Instead of limiting my analysis to these, I took the initiative to explore what other issues were involved with bringing a new customer on board. I discovered six other processes that were not part of the original plan for the project. After careful analysis, it turned out that two of these were critical. By adjusting and improving these, along with some other changes, the onboarding process was accelerated and customer retention was increased.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "A a Data Scientist, how do you employ statistics to analyze data and develop business recommendations?", "answers": ["Data Scientists use a variety of tools, statistics being one of the most used and commonly employed. An interviewer will ask this question early in the interview to set the stage, learn more about your skills and experience, and to guide you toward other, more specific questions. Keep this in mind when responding to this question, because it will provide you with the opportunity to move the interview in a direction that you are comfortable with and can easily address.", "\"Statistics is probably one of the strongest tools a Data Scientist has in their arsenal. It helps us to identify patterns, find hidden insights and quickly analyze large data sets. Statistics provide information about consumer behavior, interests, engagement and other aspects of the shopping and purchase process. They also allow for the quick development of models that validate assumptions and inferences.\"", "\"Of all the tools I use in the process of analyzing data, statistics is my favorite. This is the most mature methodology in the field of data science and there are a great many programs at our disposal. Statistical analysis is a straight forward way to identify trends, confirm a hypothesis, expose hidden insights and develop models business users need to make intelligent decisions. Statistics can be used to narrow the focus of an analysis and provide the users with the exact information they are looking for.\"", "\"To explain in simple words statistics is the mathematical tool to perform analysis and data presentation. As a data scientist and data analyst, I have frequently used statistics invalidating the hypothesis, finding trends, identifying the correlation and associations between factors, looking for hidden insights, describing data with the help of 5 point summary, etc.\"", "Great job! You have clearly explained what statistics is and how it is typically used in data analysis. Perfect!"]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "What is Data Cleansing and why is it important in Data Analysis?", "answers": ["Technical questions like this one are straight forward ways for the interviewer to explore and confirm your technical competencies related to the position for which they are interviewing you. Your preparation for an interview should include researching and practicing technical questions, in addition to general and behavioral questions. Always answer technical questions succinctly, without embellishment or additional information.", "\"Data cleansing is the process of ensuring that data obtained from a wide variety of sources is suitable for analysis. It involves a high-level review of the data set, detection of any anomalies or inaccuracies, and correcting these to ensure the data is correct and accurate. It can also be used to eliminate components of the data that are irrelevant to the analysis being performed.\"", "\"It is always a good idea to cleans data before analyzing it. This involves reviewing the data for inaccuracies, irrelevant information or other items that will skew the analysis and result in conclusions that are incorrect or not usable. When performing a data cleansing operation, the Data Scientist looks for outliers or information that doesn't fit the pattern of the majority of the data.  Inaccuracies are corrected and information not relevant to the analysis being performed is removed.\"", "\"As the name suggests, data cleansing of the process of cleaning the data so that it is in the form on which the data can be analyzed.\r\nData Cleaning involves a high-level review of the data set and looks for the missing and inconsistent data, outliers, detect noise and inaccuracies, and correcting them to make sure the data is accurate. For me, data cleansing is the most crucial step in the data analysis and I spend lots of my data analysis time at this step because it is the foundation of the whole analysis. As I read somewhere and also believe that \"garbage data gives garbage result,  Good data gives good results.'\"", "This is an excellent response because it is on point and extremely thorough. The interviewer will appreciate that you recognize the importance of data cleansing and that without it the results of the analysis won't be accurate. Great job!"]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "Can you describe how Data Analysis is used by businesses and other organizations?", "answers": ["While this appears to be another Technical Question, it is actually more of a General Question. The interviewer is likely to ask this early in the interview to help establish a conversational tone for the interview and develop some avenues to follow up questions. As with any interview question, your answer should relate to the company's operations and how you believe they use data analytics to run their business. You can usually determine this from the information provided on their website and in the job posting.", "\"As a Data Scientist, I've come across many examples of how businesses use data analysis to improve the results of their operations. For example, eCommerce firms can use data analysis to understand customer behavior, reduce churn and better target their marketing. Financial organizations use it to evaluate investment opportunities and detect fraud. Healthcare companies employ data analysis to develop treatments for specific groups of patients.\"", "\"Data analytics is one of the most significant developments in making businesses and other organizations more efficient and effective. The insight data science provides helps virtually every organization to improve its operations through a better focus on outcomes and more targeted information used for intelligent decision making. Examples of this include search engines ranking pages depending on the specific interests of the user, and social media filtering information which the user is not interested in. Another use of data analytics is in robotics, which uses machine learning to handle new situations not previously encountered. Finally, businesses can extract information from large and unstructured sets of data which can then be used to develop products and target their marketing.\"", "\"Data Analysis provides the decision support system to a business where businesses can make rational decisions and action plans based on the facts extracted from analyzing data. To explain it by an example from the financial industry,  data can be analyzed to find the trends related to sales numbers, to measure advertising efficacy, transportation costs, or wages versus productivity.\r\nIn simple words, any piece of data that could be used to make a business decision is potentially within the spectrum of a data analysis.\"", "Excellent answer! You're right that businesses use data to make decisions that can impact everything from sales, advertising, transportation, wages, etc. Your answer is thorough and smart. Nice job!"]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "What programming languages do you have experience using? Of these, which do you have the most experience with? Which do you have the least experience with?", "answers": ["This is another technical question geared toward determining your hard skills and qualifications for the data scientist position. This is relatively easy to answer since you need these skills and experience to work in this industry. Your answer should be honest, straight forward and brief. This Tick the Box question is required, but likely won't differentiate you from other candidates.", "\"I'm experienced in the majority of the major programming languages including Python, R, Java SQL, C++, and Scala. Of these, I prefer Python, due to its applicability to a wide variety of tasks and its general acceptance in the data science community.  I also like the fact that it is an open-source language and the syntax is easy to understand.\"", "\"While Python is my favorite programing language to work with, I'm also skilled in R, Java, SQL, C++, Tableau and most of the other popular languages. While each of these has its merits, Python offers the most flexibility, is easy to learn and understand, and is popular among the data science community. Another language that is becoming ubiquitous in the field is RapidMiner. I've recently learned this and I'm starting to use it more due to its robust features.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "To be a successful Data Scientist, many in the industry believe it is important to keep up-to-date on the newest technologies and methodologies. What new data-related technology/methodology have you heard of that you wish you could learn more about?", "answers": ["In many fields, people become compliant the longer they are in the field and they tend not to stay abreast of developments in the field. However, Data Science is a relatively new and quickly developing industry and Data Scientists my stay abreast of emerging technologies and methodologies. You should be able to demonstrate your curiosity and efforts to stay up to date on developments in the industry.  You also need to make sure you can discuss the technologies you mention if the interviewer asks you any follow up questions.", "\"Since our field is moving so quickly, it is very important to the time to learn about new developments and technologies which will help me do my job better. Key trends I'm currently following include Augmented Analytics, Continuous Intelligence, Explainable AI and Data Fabrics. The one technology I'm most interested in is Blockchain. While this is most associated with cryptocurrency, there are many other applications for blockchain technology and the applications for this are still in their infancy.\"", "\"One of the benefits of being a Data Scientist is the ability to learn something new every day. Our field is evolving so quickly that there is always a new technology or methodology to explore. The challenge is to not get distracted by the shiny objects one finds in the literature and on the internet, offering new and better ways to analyze data. Some of the technologies I'm currently exploring include Persistent Memory Servers, which offer better performance at a lower cost, and Graph Analytics, which allow for comparing the relationships between organizations, people and transactions.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "The work of a Data Scientist can have a large impact on the strategy, and ultimately success, of a business. Is there a time you felt your work as a Data Scientist had a profound impact on strategy development? Explain your role and contribution.", "answers": ["Organizations generally hire workers for one reason; Their ability to contribute to the attainment of the company's business objectives. This question is meant to determine if you understand the impact your role has on the organizations you work for. It will also help the interviewer to learn about your contributions to your previous employers. You should provide specific examples and quantify the benefits.", "\"Data Science has had a profound impact on businesses and their decision-making process. This practice helps businesses make quicker and more accurate decisions, communicate their products' benefits better, encourage innovation and explore new ideas. In my current role, I was involved in a prototyping project which employed data science methodology to quickly investigate new revisions of the software we were developing, without having to take the time to actually write, debug and test the code. This led to us determining the best path to take to develop the software our customers needed and would be willing to pay for and reduced the development cycle by over 50%.\"", "\"Data Science is revolutionizing the way businesses develop strategies, create new products, make decisions and interact with their customers.  Data Science and Machine Learning reduce product development cycles and accelerate the decision making process. In my last job we were faced with a situation in which there were three distinct new business opportunities the company could pursue.  Historically, analyzing, discussing and choosing the option to pursue would have taken months, during which time the situation would have changed and the original data and assumptions may no longer have been valid. However, by using data science methodologies and machine learning technology, we were able to analyze each option and present our findings and recommendations to senior management within 4 weeks. The company adopted our suggestions and the new business unit was established and became profitable within its first year of operations.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "What data visualization tools do you have experience using? Which one is your favorite to use and why?", "answers": ["This question is similar to the one about statistical software programs in that it is attempting to discover your technical knowledge and your familiarity with the tools the company you are interviewing with uses. Again, the best response is a direct one, stating your knowledge of software tools, your preference and the reason for your opinions.", "\"Data visualization tools I use include Google Charts, Tableau, Grafana, Chartist.js, FusionCharts, Datawrapper, Infogram, ChartBlocks, and D3.js. I prefer Tableau because it offers a variety of visualization styles, is easy to use, and can handle large data sets. The other reason I like Tableau is that their help desk is very responsive and open to suggestions from the user community. It isn't a true open-source software, but the product is continuously being improved by the developers and the company's customers.\"", "\"There are many data visualization tools available and I've used quite a few of them. They include Google Charts, Tableau, Grafana, Chartist.js, FusionCharts, Datawrapper, Infogram, ChartBlocks, and D3.js. My favorite is Google Charts. This is because it is easy to use, robust, widely accepted and the licensing fees are low.  Another reason I prefer Google Charts is that it can be customized to make it better suited to the specific project I'm working on. Since most of the work I do is similar, once I have tailored the tool to my needs I don't have to reconfigure it each time I use it.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "Describe a time when you had to present findings/recommendations to a non-technical audience (very little or no background in data or databases). What strategies did you use to ensure the audience did not get confused and clearly understood the message?", "answers": ["This is another example of a Behavioral Question and you can use the STAR framework to organize your answer.  The interviewer is interested in learning about your communication skills and style. Walk them through your answer systematically, describing how you communicate complex issues in a clear and non-technical manner.", "\"While Data Science is a complex and highly technical field, the people who use the information I provide are usually experts in fields other than data. Therefore, when I present my findings, I work hard to communicate them in terminology the audience is familiar with, focusing on the conclusions and recommendations rather than the data, statistics, and analysis methodology. This approach results in the organization attaining the business objective of the analysis. I also prepare myself to answer questions about the science behind the analysis if necessary.\"", "\"It is easy to get distracted by the nuances of data analysis when presenting findings of a project I've worked on to the decision-makers from other parts of the organization. This is because I'm most comfortable with the data and the analysis and may not be familiar with the other operational aspects of the company. When preparing to present to a non-technical audience, I take the time to understand how my findings and recommendations will be used, the priorities of my listeners, and the desired outcome of the meeting. I then focus on communicating clearly, and concisely, using terminology I know the audience is familiar with and understands.\""]}, {"topic": "Data+Scientist", "question": "In your past positions, have you had experience contributing to the improvement of data analysis processes, database management, data infrastructure, or anything along those lines? If so, please explain your contributions.", "answers": ["Keep in mind that organizations hire people to help them achieve their objectives. This question is seeking to learn about the past contributions you made in your previous positions and to explore whether these are similar to the challenges their company is facing. You should understand the issues the company routinely faces from your pre-interview research. Make sure your answer to this question aligns with the needs of the employer.", "\"In my most recent role, I introduced my team to new data visualization techniques to enable us to perform the data analysis faster and more accurately. It also enabled us to communicate our findings to the other business stakeholders in a manner which they could easily understand and relate to.\"", "\"One of the key objectives for any job I have had is continuous process improvement. Early on I realized that investing some of my time in pursuit of making the work I did more productive would benefit both me and the organization I worked for.  An example of this was while working with my previous employer. After learning how they currently collected, processed, cleaned and analyzed their data, I researched different tools and methodologies that would improve the process. I developed a set of recommendations and presented them to senior management. They agreed with my assessment and moved forward to implement my suggestions. As a result, the time to complete an average data analysis project was reduced by 40% and the results were more accurate.\""]}]